<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dauids strait A sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse, Iuly 8. 1621. By Samuel Buggs Bachelor of Diuinitie, sometime Fellow of Sidney-Sussex Colledge in Cambridge: and now minister of the word of God in Couentrie.</title>
            <author>Buggs, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7288</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17142)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1340:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dauids strait A sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse, Iuly 8. 1621. By Samuel Buggs Bachelor of Diuinitie, sometime Fellow of Sidney-Sussex Colledge in Cambridge: and now minister of the word of God in Couentrie.</title>
                  <author>Buggs, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Nathanael Butter, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the pyde Bull neare S. Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> MAIOR of the City of <hi>Couentry:</hi> and the reſt, Worſhipfull Aldermen, and Sheriffes of that INCORPORATION: <hi>S. B.</hi> wiſheth encreaſe of grace in this life, and aſſurance of glory in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I firſt deliuered that ſmall Treatiſe by word of mouth, it was the fartheſt part of my thought, euer to aduenture the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall of it to the view of any, as conſidering mine owne <hi>weaknes</hi> and the <hi>worlds peeuiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> But it fared with this <hi>Sermon</hi> as with a <hi>Meteor,</hi> which being gently drawne vp by
<pb facs="tcp:7288:2"/>the kindly heate of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> reſides for a time in the <hi>Ayre,</hi> and hath there indeed a <hi>bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but <hi>ſhineth</hi> not, till <hi>kindled</hi> by the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſis</hi> and circumſtant <hi>cold</hi> of the ayre: So this my Labour receiuing ſome warmth and beeing, by the gentle breath, and vndeſerued ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of ſome, was not yet ſeene of the world, vntill it tooke fire by ſome, who being (at the deliuery of it) <hi>circumſtant,</hi> did in their cauſleſſe and vndeſerued humours, giue ſuch cold entertainment vnto both it and me, that I was by the vulgar reported to bee taken by the great <hi>Fleet,</hi> or at the leaſt ſhrewdly encountred. Whereupon I thought it fit (for mine owne defence, and ſatisfaction of others) that the things before <hi>demiſla per au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> ſhould be now, <hi>oculis ſubiect a fidelibus,</hi> that what was before in the <hi>aire</hi> and in the <hi>eare,</hi> ſhould now be in the <hi>eye,</hi> that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Reader</hi> may iudge whether it deſerued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe or cenſure, yea, or no: and whether herein I haue <hi>laboured to keepe a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience toward God and men,</hi> I appeale to the iudgements of them, who being cleare of any
<pb facs="tcp:7288:2"/>thing againſt which I might ſeeme to inueigh, are fitteſt and the onely <hi>competent Iudges</hi> in this kind. Your Worſhips can (I truſt) beare me witneſſe, that I neuer amongst you for theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, haue ſhewed my ſelfe any way to be of a <hi>factious</hi> and a <hi>turbulent</hi> ſpirit, but haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies laboured and prayed for the <hi>peace</hi> of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and hope to proſper the better becauſe I <hi>loue her.</hi> Now when theſe forenamed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages had cauſed me <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>willing, nilling,</hi> for my owne ſafeguard to adiudge this poore booke to <hi>be preſt</hi> (although I might haue ſeemed wiſe in choice of ſome greater <hi>patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,)</hi> I thought fitteſt to <hi>appropriate</hi> ſome part of my labours to this place, where I was <hi>borne, brought</hi> vp, and haue ſpent my dayes euer ſince I was called firſt to the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and ſo much the rather in regard of your vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued loues, which I can neyther <hi>deny</hi> nor <hi>conceale</hi> leſt I ſhould be iniurious, and alſo your godly and religious diſpoſitions (wherein this <hi>City</hi> doth equall (without flattery be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,) the moſt ciuilly gouerned, or moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently religious places of this <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7288:3"/>Such as it is it pleades in my name, and I in the name of Truth, that it may finde <hi>acceptance</hi> with your <hi>Worſhips</hi> and as many as loue the <hi>truth,</hi> and if in any thing I ſhall be blamed, I will not bee ſo preſumptuous as with <hi>Pilate,</hi> to ſay, <hi>What I haue written, I haue written;</hi> but as the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorian, <hi>If I haue done well, it is that which I deſired, but if ſlenderly and meanly, it is that which I could attaine vnto.</hi> If hereby any (taking paines to reade is) ſhall reape any benefit, it ſhall be a full ſatisfaction for my labour and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of my heart. Now the God of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> multiply his bleſsings vpon this City, that it may be happy in <hi>gouernment, holy</hi> in <hi>profeſſion,</hi> the true <hi>member</hi> of the myſticall <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> partaking the promiſes of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> euen thoſe of this life and of the life to come: Euen ſo be it Lord Ieſus. Amen, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all Chriſtian duties to be commanded, <hi>Samuel Buggs.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7288:3"/>
            <head>DAVIDS STRAIT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 SAM. 24.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And Dauid ſaid vnto Gad, I am in a great ſtrait.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a two-fold euill whereunto all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> are ſubiect as long as they liue in theſe houſes of Clay, <hi>malum culpae,</hi> and <hi>malum poenae,</hi> an euill of ſin, and an euill of puniſhment; Semblable whereunto the whole duty of man, is compriſed in theſe two words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a patient <hi>bearing</hi> of the <hi>euill of affliction,</hi> and a conſcionable <hi>forbearing</hi> the <hi>euill of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this actiue and paſſiue life (as all other <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Seruants</hi> of God) ſo <hi>Dauid a man after his owne heart</hi> was much exerciſed, wherein hee ſo carried himſelfe, that much praiſe and renown did accrew both to his worthy <hi>perſon,</hi> and holy <hi>profeſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:7288:4"/>
            <p> In the paſſiue part of his life, <hi>Qui hominum patientior, aut qui tolerantior? Meeke as a Doue</hi> in <hi>perſecution, mild as a Lambe</hi> in <hi>proſecution</hi> of his hate-worthy enemies; eſpecially toward <hi>Saul,</hi> when God had put him into his hands, hee was ſo farre from touching his perſon, as that hee was content to ſit downe with much wrong, and bee the ſole patient of vndeſerued hatred.
<note place="margin">Iames 3.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But for the actiue part, as <hi>In many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4. &amp; 12.9.</note> ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe was faulty in two maine matters: for being made King of his hopes, hee offended in the matter of <hi>Vriah</hi> the <hi>Hittite,</hi> whom he wronged in his <hi>ſecond ſelfe,</hi> defiling his wife; and after in <hi>his owne ſelfe,</hi> betraying his life, &amp; <hi>ſlaying him with the ſword of the children of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> And now againe is mentioned (to make vp his ſinnes a number,) a ſecond ſinne of <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the people,</hi> from which ſinne becauſe by diſſwaſion he would not be <hi>hindred,</hi> wrath was gone out from God, and he could not be <hi>helped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gad</hi> the <hi>Seer</hi> was ſent in the morning vnto him to propound a <hi>hard</hi> (and yet <hi>neceſſary)</hi> choice of three, and thoſe moſt fearfull euils: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Famine</hi> for three yeares, <hi>Warre</hi> for three months, <hi>Pestilence</hi> for three daies.</p>
            <p>By theſe fearfull puniſhments as by thunder, <hi>Dauid</hi> being awaked from his <hi>ſecurity,</hi> and from the <hi>wine of ſelfe-conceipt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 21.1.</note> wherewith <hi>Satan</hi> had before intoxicated him, hearing this terrible em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7288:4"/>opens his eyes, and ſeeing three ſuch fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Hell aduancing towards him, cries out in the anguiſh and bitterneſſe of a perplexed ſoule, <hi>I am in a great ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which few words, though may ſeeme at the firſt ſight hard as the rocke in the wilderneſſe, yet haue I diſcouered flowing thereout as from <hi>Eden,</hi> foure ſeuerall ſtreames; wherein a Chriſtian may waſh like <hi>Naaman,</hi> and bee <hi>cleanſed;</hi> or like the blind man, and returne <hi>ſeeing;</hi> prouided, that waſh both hands, and head, to <hi>giue attention,</hi> and <hi>yeeld practice</hi> to the remarkable points herein contained.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Quo peccato incidit:</hi> How <hi>Dauid came</hi> into this <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Quo animo apprehenderit:</hi> How he <hi>concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> of this <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Quâ patientiâ pertulerit:</hi> How he <hi>bare</hi> this <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Quâ prudentiâ cuaſerit:</hi> How he <hi>gate out</hi> of this <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is for <hi>admonition:</hi> the ſecond for <hi>inſtruction:</hi> the third for <hi>imitation:</hi> the fourth for <hi>conſolation:</hi> Euery of them being compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by your Chriſtian wiſedome, as by the Art of the cunning Apothecarie, may either ſerue as an <hi>Antidote</hi> to preuent ſinne, or a <hi>Cordiall</hi> to ſuch as haue ſurfetted on the <hi>ſowre grape of Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This text is then a fit place for a Preacher of <hi>Repentance,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:7288:5"/>for here <hi>is much water,</hi> wherein if I ſhall wade but ſhallow, it is not that I feare to wet my feet, (for to doe any good <hi>I am yours as you are Chriſts,)</hi> but I haue iuſt cauſe to feare that either ſome ſtormes of your moleſted patience, or my fainting heart through mine owne weakneſſe, may ſinke both me and my poore meditations to the bottome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>How Dauid fell into this ſtraite:</hi> Some there haue beene who as they were ignorant of the worlds <hi>originall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phyſ.</hi> 1.</note> ſo alſo of the <hi>rule and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the ſame; and did therefore father many particular paſſages vpon fatall <hi>neceſsity.</hi> But <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> and the reſt which followed <hi>Etiam comite ratione,</hi> did ſoundly confute and worthily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plode this their error, as finding a neceſſity of the dependance of all <hi>effects</hi> vpon ſome certaine <hi>cauſes,</hi> which yet they being but <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> diſcerned onely to be naturall. But we who haue the true <hi>proſpectiue glaſſe</hi> of the <hi>word of God,</hi> may eaſily diſcerne, though a farre off, a <hi>ſupreme power</hi> guiding and ruling all particular occurrences whatſoeuer,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>to the fall of a ſparrow from the houſe,</hi> or <hi>a haire from our heads,</hi> which as it hath an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in all things, ſo alſo in this <hi>ſtrait</hi> of <hi>Dauid:</hi> that as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is in this place and I knew it not;</hi> ſo the Lord had a hand in this <hi>ſtrait,</hi> though men be not aware of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For warre,</hi> I know it is oftentimes the curſed iſſue of <hi>boundleſſe ambition,</hi> as it was in <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7288:5"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Vnus Pellaeo iuueni non ſufficit orbis</l>
                  <l>Aeſtuat infaelix anguſto limite mundi.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iuu. Sat.</hi> 10.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Or as in the <hi>Romanes</hi> that they might be <hi>rerum Domini;</hi> or as in the proud race of <hi>Ottoman,</hi> now aduancing his <hi>Moony ſtandards</hi> in <hi>Polonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or elſe it may bee conceiued by the ſeed of <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi> as in <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> the <hi>Epyrote, Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> to grow rich by the ſpoile of others, as though <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> had giuen them the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation of all. Or elſe this fire may bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by <hi>colliſion</hi> of <hi>ſlint</hi> and <hi>ſteele,</hi> as in <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leuy</hi> to reuenge the rape of <hi>Dinah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.25. 1 Sam. 15.</note> or as in <hi>Saul</hi> who ſmote the <hi>Amalekites</hi> for a former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie proffered to the wandring <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> But at this time there was no <hi>warre</hi> in hand, or if there had, the <hi>arme of Iſrael</hi> and his <hi>bow was ſo ſtrong,</hi> that had Almighty God ſtood but as an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpectator, <hi>the glory</hi> could not in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity haue <hi>departed from Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>For Famine,</hi> it may proceed from the ſupine <hi>negligence</hi> of a people who had rather <hi>begge</hi> then <hi>labour,</hi> yea, almoſt <hi>ſterue</hi> then <hi>labour,</hi> and ſo liue idlely, <hi>quaſi per ſe daret omnia tellus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> or elſe when ſome ſhall <hi>labour,</hi> and others eate the <hi>labours</hi> of their <hi>hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 6.11.</note> When <hi>Gideons</hi> wheat without hiding ſhall feed <hi>Midian,</hi> or the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> and <hi>Sabaeans</hi> ſpoile <hi>Iob</hi> of his Cattell and prouiſion.
<note place="margin">Iob 1.15.17.</note> Or by the horrible <hi>gluttony, drunkenneſſe,</hi> and <hi>exceſſe</hi> of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7288:6"/>time by <hi>prodigious &amp; prodigall</hi> vſage of the good creatures of God,
<note place="margin">Acts 11.28.</note> as it came to paſſe in the daies of <hi>Claudius Caeſar,</hi> of whom <hi>Xiphiline</hi> reports that he was wont <hi>indulgere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uiuiis effuſiſsimè.</hi> But there was now no <hi>Famine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vita Claudii.</note> that for the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> being ſtaied by attonement, as appeares, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2 1. The land now gaue her increaſe, and <hi>abounding</hi> (as it did) <hi>with milke and honey,</hi> might bee a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>Cornucopia</hi> to relieue all the families of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> So that neither <hi>nature</hi> on the one ſide, nor <hi>men</hi> on the other were like to be the cauſe of this <hi>ſtrait:</hi> this by way of probability.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> when I conſider this laſt <hi>plague</hi> and puniſhment, although there may be ſome natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon of it giuen, yet this comming ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly without any preuious diſpoſition of aire, or bodies; I cannot but conclude that it was an immediate arrow ſhot from Gods quiuer, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè opus et digitus Dei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 3.6.</note> Nor could <hi>this</hi> kind of <hi>euill haue beene in the City if the Lord himſelfe had not wrought it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This makes the meaſure of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſorrow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>preſſed downe,</hi> now to <hi>runne ouer</hi> when he apprehends not onely the <hi>Starres</hi> of heauen to fight againſt him,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.20.</note> as they did againſt <hi>Siſera,</hi> but euen the Lord of heauen with his owne <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>ſtretched out arme:</hi> Hee whoſe <hi>valour</hi> whilome laughed at the ſterne viſage of <hi>Goliah,</hi> feare and trembling is now come vpon him, and ſorrow <hi>as vpon a woman in trauaile:</hi> with an enemie hee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7288:6"/>might <hi>fight</hi> or from him <hi>flee,</hi> but now ſeeing it is God with whom he cannot <hi>fight,</hi> from whom he cannot <hi>flee.</hi> Now he is in <hi>a great ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſhall not the Iudge of all the world doe right?
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> Indeed in Gods eternall predeſtination and election, no man ought to enquire; as why <hi>Iacob</hi> is <hi>loued,</hi> and <hi>Eſau hated,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.13.</note> becauſe the <hi>Potter may doe with the clay as he liſteth.</hi> But if the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion be made in this particular, it ſhall fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that God ſought no quarrell againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor ſought occaſion to deuoure or waſt the <hi>ſheepe of his pasture.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 7.13.</note> Why was <hi>Iſrael</hi> diſcomfitted at <hi>Ai?</hi> was there not an <hi>execrable thing amongst them?</hi> Why did both wind and water conſpire the wracke of <hi>Ionah?</hi> was not he <hi>profugus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ion. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away</hi> from God? <hi>Pone poenam ſupponis culpam.</hi> For ſurely the mercy of God being ſo great in <hi>pardoning</hi> ſinne when it is <hi>committed,</hi> may fully perſwade vs that he will neuer <hi>puniſh</hi> till it be <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Propter me haec tempeſtas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ionah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionah 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Propter me haec peſtis,</hi> may <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay; vntill man be <hi>actor</hi> of ſinne, God is neuer <hi>author</hi> of <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.30. Oſ. 13.9.</note> The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> houſe fals not vpon <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> vnleſſe <hi>his owne hands pull it downe. Iſraels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is</hi> not but of her ſelfe: <hi>Non tellus cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam tellurem cymba reliquit,</hi> For as <hi>Adam</hi> had not beene mortall, had he not beene ſinfull, no more ſhould his poſterity euer ſmart but by the ſore of <hi>ſinne.</hi> When ſinne is finiſhed if we haue not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to glorifie Gods <hi>mercy</hi> in <hi>pardoning</hi> vs we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7288:7"/>ſhall be compelled to acknowledge his <hi>iuſtice</hi> in <hi>puniſhing</hi> vs.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theorem.</hi> 1.</note> Hence obſerue, that <hi>preuious ſinne is alwaies the cauſe of ſubſequent miſery,</hi> yea, it is <hi>proprium, omni, ſoli</hi> (though not <hi>ſemper</hi>) to haue <hi>ſinne</hi> the <hi>prodromus,</hi> the fore-runner of <hi>iudgement,</hi> and the onely <hi>prologue</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Tragedy</hi> of one man, or the generall ruine of many: Had not <hi>Dauid</hi> numbred <hi>Iſrael, Gad</hi> had not <hi>threatned</hi> it, God had not <hi>puniſhed</hi> it.</p>
            <p>The Heathen themſelues could ſo farre iuſtifie their ſuppoſed gods in this kind as to confeſſe that when <hi>ſinne</hi> preuailed, not before:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hor. Carm. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Od.</hi> 3.</note> — Macies &amp; noua febrium</l>
                  <l>Terris incubuit cohors</l>
                  <l>Semoti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> priùs tarda neceſsitas</l>
                  <l>Lethi corripuit gradum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Had not the old world ſwomme in ſecurity and <hi>Epicuriſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.13.</note> they had not floated in that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deluge.
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.20.</note> Had not <hi>Sodome</hi> beene tainted with ſo filthy ſinnes, they had not felt ſo fierie a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.
<note place="margin">Luke 19.42.43.</note> Had <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſeene the day of their <hi>viſitation,</hi> it had not ſeene the day of <hi>deſolation.</hi> Had not <hi>Dauid</hi> committed ſome great <hi>ſinne</hi> hee had neuer beene in this <hi>great ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Pilate</hi> heard the people cry out to haue Chriſt crucified,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.23.</note> hee asketh in the audience of them all, <hi>What euill hath he done?</hi> So <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> may heere demand in <hi>Dauids</hi> behalfe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7288:7"/>
               <hi>Quid mali admiſit?</hi> Why will God thus vexe and perplexe at the heart a man <hi>after his owne heart:</hi> the Text anſwers hereunto, verſe 1. <hi>Dauid had numbred the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Numbring of people</hi> was vſed in ancient time by <hi>Sergius Tullus</hi> the Romane,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liu. Aul. Gel. lib.</hi> 10.</note> to know how many were fit for warre, and the age amongſt them was from 17. to 46. and in dangerous times till 50. and our Sauiour Chriſt commendeth a <hi>wiſe King who will forecaſt whether he be able to meet his enemy or not.</hi> Beſide,
<note place="margin">Luke 14 31.</note> they were numbred by <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 38. and againe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 1. why might not then an action <hi>repeated</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and daily <hi>practiſed</hi> by other Princes be as lawfull for <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall <hi>Dauid fight Gods battailes,</hi> and not know the ſtrength of his army? <hi>or goe in and out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a people,</hi> and not know the number of them? and thus the <hi>verdict</hi> of <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> returnes <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus, We find no fault at all in this man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay a while fond opinion, and take this in charge, <hi>That a thing lawfull, nay, good in it ſelfe, may in the manner or end of doing, become vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and ſo a <hi>ſinne:</hi> For <hi>Omne quod non licet eſt peccatum. Prayer</hi> is commanded, and beſt if it be done <hi>in a corner, that no man may ſee it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.2.</note> but if in the <hi>corners</hi> of the <hi>ſtreet, that all men may ſee,</hi> it is <hi>abhominable. Almes</hi> are commended, yet the noyſe of <hi>a trumpet blowne before them,</hi> drownes all their worth, and leaues them <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7288:8"/>and no better. Are things ſo good ſo ſoone tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bad? How then are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues neyther good nor bad? Faſting is good if it be done to <hi>tame the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>bring it in ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> but if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bee admixed, <hi>to be ſeene of men</hi> it is <hi>hypocriſie.</hi> If a man out of the weakneſſe of his iudgement, ſhall refuſe a ceremony or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, as fearing to wound his ſoule by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting idolatry, I pitty his caſe, his action being to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, but if any <hi>ſtiffe-necked</hi> or <hi>ſtiffe-hammed</hi> Schiſmaticke ſhall doe it, out of oppoſition to the order and diſcipline of the Church, his holy <hi>ſingularity</hi> is no better then ſtubbornnes and deep <hi>hypocriſie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe.</note> Herein then <hi>Dauid</hi> failed. Firſt, it was needleſſe, hauing no warre in hand. Secondly, it was a curious crotchet, <hi>ideò numeratur vt nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi> onely to know. Thirdly, it ſauoured of pride to glory in the number of the people, which three circumſtances being weighed in the <hi>ballance of the Sanctuary,</hi> proued in <hi>Gods eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Dauids owne confeſsion,</hi> verſe 10. <hi>a ſinne, a wickedneſſe, an exceeding folly:</hi> nor could hee charge God iuſtly of any iniuſtice, for bringing of him into this great <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee that came not by <hi>fate,</hi> but from God; it came not <hi>vniuſtly,</hi> but for <hi>ſinne,</hi> and this ſinne by name was, <hi>numbring of the people.</hi> Now the manner of <hi>Dauids</hi> falling into this <hi>ſtrait,</hi> ſtands like a pillar of <hi>Salt</hi> for our <hi>remembrance</hi> and <hi>inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>he that runneth</hi> may plainly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7288:8"/>reade this for his obſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That a faire Saint may fall into a foule ſinne, nor can the beſt man carry himſelfe ſo equally with God, but that ſometimes by ſinne he fals into his lurch, and becomes liable to puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Dauids</hi> part, were not his heart ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dide as to confeſſe the truth, we may deale with him, <hi>obſignatis tabulis,</hi> namely Gods faithfull Regiſter, the <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> which doth <hi>charge</hi> and <hi>challenge</hi> him of a former, and a fouler ſinne in the matter of <hi>Vriah</hi> the <hi>Hittite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.</note> whoſe blood (like the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> the innocent) could wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt him: But what need we any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther witneſſe, ſeeing <hi>we haue heard of his owne mouth</hi> in that <hi>poenitentiary Pſal.</hi> 51. wherein he ſheds many teares for ſhedding of onely this mans blood.</p>
            <p>But leſt I ſhould by <hi>one Swallow</hi> to proue a <hi>Summer,</hi> and for one mans ſinne to <hi>condemne the generation of the iuſt:</hi> although I deſire not to vncouer the ſhame of the <hi>Saints,</hi> yet fith <hi>all things are writen for our inſtruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> giue me leaue to ſhew ſome ſpots and moales which haue been no ſmall blemiſh to their perfection. Amongſt the <hi>twelue</hi> there was but <hi>one Iudas,</hi> one <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>perdition,</hi> but one that <hi>burſt his bowels with a fall;</hi> but none of the reſt eſcaped without a fall. To omit the ambition of <hi>Zebedees</hi> ſonnes,
<note place="margin">Marke 10.37. Iohn 20.25.</note> the <hi>incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity</hi> of <hi>Thomas,</hi> the <hi>doubting</hi> of the <hi>two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples,</hi> come wee to the Papiſts maſter-peece,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7288:9"/>their Dominicall letter of the Apoſtles; <hi>Peter</hi> is reproued for <hi>tempting</hi> his Maſter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22. recorded for <hi>denying</hi> him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.70. and all the Diſciples ſeeing their Maſter apprehended in the Garden, for feare forſooke him and fled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.56.</p>
            <p>Nor was this <hi>Leproſie</hi> a new diſeaſe in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, or like <hi>Ionahs goord, come vp in a night,</hi> but if wee ſhall vſe the Hiſtorians <hi>optich glaſſe,</hi> we ſhall diſcouer a farre off as in a <hi>Landſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>Noah</hi> lye <hi>drunken</hi> in his Tent, <hi>and naked too,</hi> did not his good ſonnes <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iapheth</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, <hi>Immerſus aquâ vino mergitur:</hi> Neither did any leſſe happen to <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe righteous ſoule was vexed at the vncleane conuerſation of the <hi>Sodomites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.7.</note> the onely man thought worthy to be pluckt out of the fire of <hi>Sodome; Intactus igne vrit libidine,</hi> and his drunkenneſſe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſinne,
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.36.</note> which <hi>(had there beene one righteous man in Sodome,)</hi> his ſoule would tremble to haue committed it.</p>
            <p>To call the life or <hi>wiſedome</hi> of <hi>Salomon</hi> in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in mee, it were but <hi>folly,</hi> and yet no more then he committed, who by the multitude of his <hi>Dalilahs</hi> ſuffered his heart to bee ſtolne away from God.
<note place="margin">Lorinus praef. in Act.</note> 
               <hi>Tenorius</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king queſtion whether <hi>Salomon</hi> was ſaued or damned, cauſed his picture to be drawne in his Chappell <hi>halfe in heauen,</hi> and <hi>halfe in hell:</hi> this was about his ſtate of <hi>glory.</hi> But ſhould my rude
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7288:9"/>pencill delineate him in the ſtate of <hi>grace,</hi> I would both picture him and all the reſt of Gods people, halfe in heauen, and halfe in earth, <hi>in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> by reaſon of their holy and <hi>heauenly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, in heauen</hi> by reaſon of their <hi>aſſurance of glory and ſaluation:</hi> but <hi>on earth</hi> by reaſon of that <hi>body of ſinne</hi> and <hi>death</hi> which they carry about them, hauing the fleſh <hi>preſsing</hi> with <hi>continuall fight,</hi> and <hi>oppreſsing with often conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> made choice of ſome of the children of the Captiuity to ſtand before him, he commanded to bring ſuch as were of <hi>the Kings ſeed, and of the Princes, well fauoured, and without blemiſh. Si verbis audacia detur,</hi> giue me leaue to apply this. God the King of heauen hath out of his meere mercy choſen out of <hi>Satans cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity</hi> ſome to ſtand before him, they are of the <hi>Kings ſeed,</hi> and of <hi>the Princes, ſonnes of God and brethren of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cant. 15.</note> 
               <hi>faire</hi> they are and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, the <hi>chiefe among ten thouſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Free from the vſuall deformities, but onely they are ſometimes troubled with the <hi>falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> witneſſe the examples before mentioned; and the <hi>fall</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> into this <hi>great ſtrait;</hi> not that the <hi>Protoplaſtes</hi> of our ſpirituall feature and perfection were the cauſe of this, but euen that <hi>originall ſinne</hi> and <hi>corruption,</hi> which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>coeuterine</hi> with vs, pluckes vs by the heele as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> did <hi>Eſau,</hi> and pinches them as the Angell did <hi>Iacob</hi> in the thigh,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.25.26.</note> that they neuer claw off this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7288:10"/>halting ſo long as they liue in <hi>theſe houſes of clay:</hi> I learned this leſſon of <hi>Salomon,</hi> that <hi>God made man vpright, but he ſought many inuentions. Adam</hi> was taught a tricke by the Diuell to <hi>loſe his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> who was before at large, is now taught by Satan, and brought by him into this <hi>ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although by ſuch enormities of the Saints there cannot but accrew <hi>diſhonour</hi> to God, <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>ſcandall</hi> to their <hi>profeſsion,</hi> and <hi>euill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> to the infecting of others. Yet Almighty God who brought light out of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> life out of <hi>death,</hi> can alſo bring <hi>good</hi> out of <hi>euill;</hi> and like a wiſe <hi>Architect</hi> can ſo diſpoſe of euery peece, (except thoſe for the fire) as to build a glorious <hi>Temple</hi> for the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, hereby is laid the foundation of <hi>humility</hi> in the hearts of men. The aduenturous Chriſtian when he heares of the two Tables of Gods <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.3. Mat 19.20. and 25.25.</note> thinkes he can carry them as eaſily as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the gates of <hi>Azzah,</hi> and ſay, Lord thou <hi>haſt thine owne, all theſe haue I kept from my youth.</hi> But finding at the length, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that <hi>his ſtrength is but as other mens,</hi> he is ſtricken as low as the <hi>Center,</hi> and ſhrinks to an <hi>Acome</hi> in his owne conceipt: Now being brought to this ebbe he is a good foundation for God to build vpon: now growing conſcious of his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities (like <hi>Peter</hi> walking vpon the water) he cries, <hi>Maſter ſaue me,</hi> now hee will no more of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7288:10"/>his owne ſtrength, but onely of the <hi>grace</hi> of God, which is <hi>onely ſufficient</hi> for him. The Swans of Thames and Po, beholding with a retorted neck their goodly feathers, thinke themſelues, <hi>Rarae aues in terris,</hi> but when their <hi>blacke legs</hi> and <hi>feete</hi> are become the obiects of their ſight, then they find that they are, <hi>nigris Cygnis ſimillimae:</hi> So when men behold their liues in what they are <hi>commendable,</hi> or tolerable, the Phariſee himſelfe is not more proud then they; but when they looke into the glaſſe of the Law of God, then goes the <hi>hand</hi> to the <hi>breaſt,</hi> and the <hi>word</hi> from the <hi>mouth, O God be mercifull vnto me a ſinner.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> The liues of the beſt men that liue vpon earth, are like <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzars</hi> image, hauing <hi>feet of clay</hi> as well as <hi>a head of gold:</hi> Here then is <hi>Schola &amp; ſcala coeli, a Schoole to teach a neare way,</hi> and <hi>a ladder to helpe vp the beſt way</hi> to heauen: O happy daughter of ſo vnhappy a mother, Now <hi>Nathan</hi> may bee heard if he reproue, Now <hi>Saint Peter</hi> may catch fiſh when the water is troubled, Dauid before by Sathan <hi>drawne beſide himſelfe,</hi> is now by Sin dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>out of him ſelfe,</hi> As much I conceiue of <hi>Peter,</hi> that his <hi>faint heart</hi> was now become an <hi>humble heart:</hi> and though <hi>Petrus</hi> was <hi>Petra,</hi> yet like the rocke in the wilderneſſe, he yeelded abundance of water, which makes me giue the more credence to <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> affirming of him, that hee ſpent euery morning in weeping, vntill his eyes were dimme with weeping, and deepe furrowes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7288:11"/>were plowed in his face with teares, <hi>tam vi, quam ſaepe cadendo.</hi> Oh that it may euer be ſeene, that if in the <hi>ſeruice of God,</hi> the Saints miſſe the firſt <hi>Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>integritie,</hi> they be ſure to reade and learne the <hi>ſecond Leſſon</hi> of <hi>humility: Magis enim Deo placet humilitas ex malè factis, quàm ſuperbia ex benè factis:</hi> He that exalteth himſelfe in his <hi>good deeds</hi> ſhall be <hi>humbled,</hi> but hee that ſhall <hi>humble</hi> himſelfe for his <hi>euill deeds</hi> ſhall be <hi>exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This falling of the Saints into ſinne, though <hi>caſuall</hi> and <hi>vnuſuall,</hi> doth worke in them a caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and carefull carriage in the ſequell of their liues: danger is the adequate obiect of feare and warineſſe, and ſinne being an auerſion of the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> from the <hi>Creator,</hi> the dangerous and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effects thereof cannot but deterre and affright the once entangled ſoule from any relaps or reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuation into the ſame. <hi>Ictus piſcis ſapit.</hi> The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, who by <hi>Sathans malice</hi> and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching policie, are brought <hi>into Sinne,</hi> and by Gods mercy brought <hi>out of it</hi> againe, do paſſe the remainder of their time, and worke out their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation <hi>in feare and trembling.</hi> The Turks now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in that (ſometimes) citie of Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">Timberl. trauel.</note> hauing an old Prophecy, that the Citie ſhall be retaken at the ſame place where before it was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted and conquered, haue in and neare that place, immured all paſſage, and preuented all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of entring: in like manner, if <hi>Sathan</hi> our mortall enemie haue heretofore made aſſault vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7288:11"/>our ſoules, and like a <hi>ſtrong man entred and ſpoiled vs:</hi> if at the priuie dore of our <hi>hearts,</hi> by ſinfull imaginations, let vs be ſure to keepe <hi>our hearts with all diligence:</hi> If at the too too <hi>open dore</hi> of our lippes by <hi>filthy communication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 141.3.</note> let vs ſet <hi>a watch before our mouth, and keepe the doore of our lips:</hi> If he ſhall enter by our eares, which often prooue careleſſe Centinels, by admitting and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining <hi>idle talke, filthy and corrupt communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, lying or ſlanderous reports,</hi> rather become like deafe men and heare not, then euer that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and malicious enemy ſhall foyle vs at the like aduantage.</p>
            <p>While <hi>thornes</hi> and <hi>weeds</hi> are ſuffered to couer the <hi>face of the ſluggards garden</hi> they muſt needes be an hinderance to the increaſe and growth of either <hi>pleaſant flower</hi> or <hi>profitable hearbe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stella 1. in Luc.</note> but if thence <hi>tranſplanted,</hi> they are placed in the hedge, they ſerue to fence the garden that the <hi>beaſts of the field</hi> annoy it not: So, while Sinne is ſuffered to haue roote in the heart of man, no increaſe of good, no <hi>hearbe</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> can be expected, as our Sauiour applies it in the Parable, wherein the thornes are ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Now if theſe thorny and <hi>ſoule-wounding</hi> ſin be remoued from the <hi>heart</hi> and affection, and placed in the <hi>memory,</hi> it will proue in ſome ſort good to Gods children to haue ſinned, for hauing felt the chaſtiſement by <hi>rods,</hi> they will tremble to thinke vpon <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,</hi> and finding Sathan ſo cruelly tyrannizing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7288:12"/>vpon a ſmall ſinne, ſo vnfaithfull in a little, they will be loath to truſt ſo <hi>bad a Counſellour,</hi> or for a great matter, commit their ſoules to ſo <hi>bad a Steward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can we thinke but <hi>Dauid</hi> was now growne more <hi>cautelous,</hi> or that if he had againe his former freedome, that Satan ſhould againe ſo haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigled him? Surely the <hi>bought wiſedome</hi> of the Saints proues good, if not the <hi>beſt:</hi> Oh that we could be made ſo wiſe by our ſins and the fruits of them, as by <hi>one</hi> to auoid <hi>many,</hi> by <hi>ſmaller</hi> to auoid <hi>greater,</hi> by the <hi>pinch of a weeſel</hi> to auoid the <hi>pawes of a Lyon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.7.</note> Conſider here <hi>what I ſay, and the Lord giue vs vnderſtanding in things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> paſſing by the field of the <hi>Sluggard</hi> obſerued <hi>nettles</hi> and <hi>thornes</hi> vpon the face of it, and he <hi>learned inſtruction,</hi> here is multiplicity of learning. <hi>What came you hither to learne? humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity?</hi> then behold what thou art without the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting grace</hi> of God, or if <hi>charity</hi> iudge here of thy falling neighbour as ſubiect to infirmity, or if further <hi>instruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> for the remainder of thy dayes, learne here <hi>to walke wiſely,</hi> and worke out thy ſaluation with <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. glorying in Gods mercy and power demands, <hi>Where now is the Scribe? where now is the diſputer of this world?</hi> And ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that I may glory likewiſe in the truth of this propoſed and proued <hi>Theorem,</hi> I demand, <hi>where now is the Papiſt? where the Pelagian?</hi> what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7288:12"/>of the <hi>Saints perfection in this life?</hi> This hereſie was bred in North-Wales, there was this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, firſt hatcht, afterward bred vp at Weſt-Babylon.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Peſtifero vomuit coluber ſermone Britannus.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Whereunto I may adde,</p>
            <q>Pestifero docuit coluber ſermone Quirinus.</q>
            <p>For the Church of Rome hauing <hi>lickt vp</hi> the vomit of this Arch-hereticke (as the Poets are fained to haue done <hi>Homers</hi>) haue ſpit forth the ſame againe, to the infection of many a ſoule. Grant we to the Church of Rome (a thing which they can neuer euince) that <hi>Peter</hi> was head of the Church, as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid to the Iewes, <hi>Behold your King,</hi> ſo ſay I to them, <hi>Behold your Peter,</hi> if his <hi>faults</hi> and <hi>falls</hi> were not like vnto other mens; Surely the <hi>foundation of the Church</hi> being thus <hi>ſhaken</hi> and the <hi>vaile</hi> of the Temple rent aſunder; I may eaſily coniecture what betides the reſt, if the caſe goe thus with the <hi>greene tree,</hi> what ſhall become of the <hi>dry tree?</hi> What coſt <hi>Peter</hi> ſo many teares? what was the cauſe of this <hi>ſtrait</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> was perfection? then God is vniuſt. No, it was <hi>imperfection,</hi> let God be <hi>iuſt</hi> and the Church of Rome a lyar: <hi>Dangerous</hi> then and <hi>damnable</hi> is their opinion, cauſing men ſo much to dreame of perfection that they neuer labour for it <hi>procul hinc.</hi> If we maintaine the <hi>bond-woman,</hi> wee muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7288:13"/>keepe her <hi>ſon,</hi> if we maintaine <hi>perfection,</hi> then alſo <hi>merits,</hi> and not onely that, but another monſtrous <hi>baſtard</hi> with ſixe fingers on a hand, <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation:</hi> certainly for <hi>perfection</hi> of Romiſh <hi>Ieſuites</hi> thus much and no more will I euer grant that they are perfect in the Popiſh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Machiauilians, abſolute</hi> traytors, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of men and <hi>matches</hi> for the Diuell. I grant them alſo to be <hi>meritorious</hi> but for all the paines they haue taken in our Engliſh vineyard, their wages haue beene ſuch as that the Hangman hath beene their pay-maſter.
<note place="margin">Gretſerus.</note> Yea, but the Pope (ſaith <hi>Gretſerus</hi>) muſt needs be holy, <hi>Si non ſanctitate propriâ, ſanctitate tamen officii:</hi> and ſo taller by head and ſhoulders then his fellowes. But if <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> plucke this ſtoole from vnder him where lies his Holineſſe then? Sure their knowledge is no more then other mens, all <hi>knowing but in part.</hi> Indeed ſome Popes knowledge was <hi>not in part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alphonſ. de Caſtro.</note> for <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro</hi> affirmes that ſome of them knew <hi>nothing at all.</hi> Their <hi>ſanctification</hi> no more then others, for though <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt were <hi>holy by vertue of his office,</hi> yet as he was <hi>Alexander</hi> he gaue his ſoule to the diuell, and ſo (by the Schoole-mens helpe) was damned with a diſtinction. Whatſoeuer the <hi>pride</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> may conceiue, or their inſolency dare maintaine, God let me euer be a member of that Church while I haue any being, which (though reformed in other things) may ſeeme deformed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7288:13"/>in this: that it acknowledgeth no particular member of it to be exempt from <hi>humane frailty,</hi> and though not ſubiect to the <hi>dominion of ſinne)</hi> yet falling many times vnder <hi>ſinnes</hi> vſurped go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and haue daily need to be renewed by <hi>repentance.</hi> Holy <hi>Dauid</hi> though in the generall courſe of his life a man with whom God was wel pleaſed, <hi>ſuo laborat naeuo;</hi> and the beſt that liues may <hi>ſemel in anno,</hi> nay, <hi>ſepties in die,</hi> fall into a <hi>great ſinne</hi> and ſo by the iuſt iudgement of God into <hi>a great ſtrait.</hi> I conclude this Theorem with this corollary. That if all the diuine and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gifts and graces of Gods holy Spirit (as <hi>wiſdome, knowledge, ſanctification, &amp;c.</hi>) were <hi>doubled vpon the head</hi> of one man (be he no more then a man) may ſinne of weakneſſe, though not of <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> and offend as <hi>grieuouſly</hi> though not ſo <hi>frequently</hi> as his brethren.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we ſeene <hi>Dauids</hi> entrance into this <hi>ſtrait,</hi> now ſee we the nature of it, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how he apprehends it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How Dauid apprehended it:</hi> As all miſery and ſorrow of it ſelfe is grieuous vnto <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> ſo ſome aboue the reſt (by the iuſt iudgement of God) is more heauy and grieuous then other, and doth more perplexe the mind of man. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the <hi>matter,</hi> if it be ſuch as is intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the <hi>manner,</hi> if it be ſuch as is ineuitable.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:7288:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Iaacobs</hi> ſeruice of ſeuen yeares for <hi>Rachel</hi> was <hi>ineuitable,</hi> yet being but a <hi>ſeruice,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,</hi> it was tolerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſeruitude in the <hi>iron fornace</hi> was <hi>intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> yet in regard of Gods promiſe to viſit them, it proued <hi>euitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the things here propounded to <hi>Dauid,</hi> in their nature, were 1. <hi>intolerable. Famine, Sword, Peſtilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God that propounded them makes them <hi>ineuitable, Chuſe one: Dauid</hi> is onely left happy in this, that though he cannot chuſe but hee muſt haue one, yet hee may chuſe which <hi>one</hi> he will haue.</p>
            <p>That we may the better apprehend the <hi>Strait</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 6.</note> I will briefely open <hi>three Seales,</hi> where wee ſhall ſee the <hi>three Furies</hi> which <hi>Gad</hi> the <hi>Seer</hi> preſents to <hi>Dauid,</hi> to take a <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>hapleſſe</hi> choiſe of either of them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt comes <hi>Famine,</hi> riding vpon a <hi>pale Horſe, killing with hunger and with death.</hi> Sometimes clad in a roabe of immoderate raine and ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, drowning the worlds <hi>plenty,</hi> and the earths <hi>prouiſion:</hi> Sometimes bearing on her ſhoulders <hi>heauens of braſſe,</hi> and treading vnder her feete the <hi>earth of iron:</hi> Sometimes attended with <hi>Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers innumerable, to eat vp the fruits of the earth.</hi> Pale, and leane ſhe is, more then the picture of death, <hi>Mors in illa,</hi> as well as <hi>mors in olla;</hi> and which is more, <hi>genus miſerabile lethi.</hi> When God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7288:14"/>who giues to man the <hi>breath of life,</hi> ſhall denie <hi>bread to maintaine life:</hi> when <hi>Winter</hi> ſhall be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>Summer,</hi> and <hi>Summer</hi> into <hi>Winter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note> when a man ſhall riſe <hi>earlie, and eate the bread of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> and at night be to <hi>care for his bread:</hi> when men ſhall <hi>Sow much, and bring in little:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1.6.</note> when the <hi>harueſt ſhall be little, and the labourers many:</hi> when one ſhall <hi>plant,</hi> another <hi>water,</hi> and God ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie increaſe: is not this a <hi>great Strait?</hi> And yet all theſe are but <hi>initia dolorum.</hi> Ah my Lord (now thinkes <hi>Dauid</hi>) ſhall theſe eyes behold my poore <hi>Iſrael, running and whining like dogs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 59</note> and cannot be ſatisfied? Shall I ſee <hi>cleanneſſe of teeth,</hi> and <hi>leanneſſe of body</hi> in all my Land? Can I endure to ſee an <hi>Aſſes head ſold for</hi> 80. <hi>pieces of ſiluer, and a cab of doues doung for</hi> 20 <hi>pieces?</hi> Shall I ſee a <hi>birth-right</hi> bidden for a <hi>meſſe of pottage,</hi> and will not be taken? Shall I behold my poore people, like <hi>Pharaohs leane kine?</hi> Shall I heare them crie, Oh giue vs bread or we periſh for hunger? Shall I ſee mothers <hi>re-womb</hi> and <hi>re-entomb</hi> the <hi>fruit of their body</hi> for want of food. Three yeeres <hi>Famine</hi> haue we felt already, and a ſecond ſiege will turn <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi> into <hi>skinne</hi> and <hi>bone;</hi> my people muſt become <hi>meat for wormes,</hi> as hauing <hi>none for themſelues:</hi> This puniſhment is <hi>greater then can be borne;</hi> This is too <hi>great</hi> a <hi>Strait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond <hi>Seale</hi> being opened, forth comes <hi>Warre,</hi> riding vpon a <hi>red Horſe,</hi> and he <hi>vnbridled:</hi> A time when all things are carried by <hi>force of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7288:15"/>Armes,</hi> and not of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> A time wherein <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus</hi> regards not the aged head of <hi>Priam,</hi> nor yet the ſacred <hi>Altar</hi> whereto he flies: A time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in old <hi>Iacobs</hi> head is ſent with <hi>ſorrow to the graue,</hi> and that not <hi>ſine caede &amp; vulnere:</hi> A time wherin <hi>Rachel</hi> may <hi>weepe for her children, and will not be comforted becauſe they are not:</hi> A time Paradoxall vnto nature, wherein <hi>Parents</hi> burie their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> A time when men muſt either <hi>fight,</hi> and ſo runne vpon a <hi>ſodaine death;</hi> or <hi>flie,</hi> and ſo lead a <hi>tedious life:</hi> A time of <hi>out-cries,</hi> of <hi>Fathers</hi> for their <hi>Children</hi> their liuely images, when <hi>Widowes</hi> weepe for their <hi>ſecond ſelues</hi> their <hi>husbands,</hi> when <hi>Orphanes</hi> lament the loſſe of <hi>Parents</hi> their onely ſtayes; when old <hi>men</hi> are <hi>comfortleſſe, wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes helpleſſe, children hapleſſe,</hi> men, women, and children, all <hi>hopeleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe had been a <hi>Man of warre</hi> from his youth, and had been eye-witneſſe of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable euents of <hi>Warre:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note> That he feared it not, witneſſe two hundred <hi>foreskinnes</hi> of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> witneſſe the fall of <hi>Goliah,</hi> witneſſe the ſons of <hi>Ammon,</hi> whom he put <hi>vnder axes, ſawes,</hi> and <hi>harrowes:</hi> Whereſoeuer he marched, <hi>death</hi> and <hi>deſtruction muſtered</hi> in his <hi>face: Saul</hi> hath ſlaine a thouſand, but <hi>Dauid</hi> his ten thouſand, this was <hi>Vox populi,</hi> and very true.</p>
            <p>Well then thinkes <hi>Dauid,</hi> I will <hi>fight three months</hi> with the proudeſt enemie that dare ſet foot vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; thus hauing thought
<pb facs="tcp:7288:15"/>he ſpeakes: Nay but <hi>Gad</hi> replies, <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou muſt not <hi>fight,</hi> but <hi>flie three months.</hi> Now then he is in a <hi>wonderfull Strait,</hi> now his <hi>troubled ſoule</hi> cannot but preſage <hi>much euill:</hi> He vſed to <hi>purſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.42.</note> and now muſt he be <hi>purſued?</hi> He did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies as ſmall as the duſt before the wind,</hi> and now <hi>he muſt flie as duſt before the wind:</hi> If it were for a day, hee might the better beare it, though the <hi>Sunne ſhould ſtand ſtill to lengthen that day:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 10.</note> but <hi>three months</hi> will make the ſtreetes of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſtreame with <hi>bloud,</hi> the people made <hi>a heape of dead bodies,</hi> and the Citie a <hi>heape of ſtones, God deſpited, the people deſtroyed,</hi> the <hi>Temple de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed:</hi> Oh then I cannot endure this <hi>wondrous Strait, Pone tertium,</hi> O man of God, let mee heare the third euill, that though I haue <hi>done wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly,</hi> I may <hi>chuſe wiſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third <hi>Seale</hi> being <hi>opened, Peſtilence</hi> iſſues forth vpon a <hi>blacke Horſe killing</hi> with <hi>ſickneſse</hi> and <hi>death.</hi> This ſeemes to be the <hi>faireſt choice,</hi> as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the immediate hand of God, and being but for <hi>three dayes,</hi> and ſo ſhorteſt of <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</hi> But yet it is a <hi>grieuous puniſhment:</hi> Storehouſes may ſerue againſt a <hi>Famine: Dauids Citie wals</hi> (or if not thoſe) his <hi>liuing walls</hi> his <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> his <hi>Worthies</hi> may <hi>meet his enemies in the gate,</hi> but <hi>Peſtilence flieth by night, and killeth at noone day.</hi> One cries, Oh my brother, come not nigh me, for I am infected: Another, barr'd in by command, ſhut vp by ſickneſſe, and (worſe) pend
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7288:16"/>in by ſorow; cries out at a window, O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, O my brother, either now breathing their laſt, or by this time dead. Some going (if any ſo dare) to the ſad funerall of their friends, before they returne to their <hi>owne home,</hi> finde their <hi>long home. O bellum Dei contrà homines:</hi> The houſe may ſhield men and cattell from the hayle, flight may ſaue from the <hi>Sword,</hi> ſoiourning in another country may preſerue from <hi>Famine,</hi> but in this contagion, at home our houſes ſtifles vs, abroad the ayre infects vs. Behold now (beloued) <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids Strait:</hi> If I ſhould ſay no more oft his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, this Citie knowes what kind of miſery it is. <hi>Etenim pars magna fuit:</hi> How was it almoſt made <hi>deſolate,</hi> and her marchandize (whilome like that of <hi>Tyrus</hi>) almoſt <hi>decayed?</hi> When hee that had walkt by night, was in more feare to haue met the dead then the liuing, A wofull time, when there ſhall be more neede to <hi>weede</hi> the pauement then to mend it; more cries of the <hi>Veſpillo, Who is here dead?</hi> then of the <hi>Tradeſ-man, What doe ye lacke?</hi> O time of deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, dulneſſe, and diſcontent! Now I beſeech you againe haue a regard of <hi>Dauids Strait,</hi> and conſider if <hi>euer ſorrow were like vnto his ſorrow, wherewith the Lord afflicted him in the day of his wrath.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> Neuer could the <hi>irons enter ſo neare to the ſoule of Ioſeph,</hi> as this ſorrow to the heart of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> See we now theſe <hi>three things</hi> propounded, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid of the pleaſures of the world, <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7288:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of vanities, and all is vanitie,</hi> ſo may <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay of the <hi>fruit of ſinne,</hi> death of deaths, and all is death. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was in <hi>a wonderfull Strait,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two, <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death; Dauid</hi> is betwixt <hi>three,</hi> and each is <hi>death; Famin a pinching death, Warre</hi> a <hi>cruell death, Peſtilence a noyſome death:</hi> Surely, <hi>a moſt wonderfull Strait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the next place that which is <hi>vltimus aerumnae cumulus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Ineuitable.</note> and makes <hi>Dauid</hi> abſolutely miſerable, that now he is like the Iſraelites that ſaw themſelues in an <hi>euill caſe,</hi> but they knew not how to helpe it.</p>
            <p>While he is thus ruminating of this <hi>hard bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Gad</hi> tarries for an anſwer, and now impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of further delay, demands a ſpeedy <hi>reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> that <hi>hee may returne an anſwer to him that ſent him.</hi> Thus then at the length out of the <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> ſorrow of his <hi>heart</hi> his trembling lips and <hi>tongue</hi> vtter theſe or the like words of <hi>paſsion.</hi> Oh man of God <hi>pray for me vnto the Lord, that if it be poſsible this pride of my heart may be forgiuen me:</hi> Oh carry God my <hi>ſighes</hi> and <hi>teares,</hi> perhaps that <hi>ſweet incenſe</hi> may <hi>appeaſe</hi> him. Preſent vnto my louing God my <hi>ſtraitned ſoule,</hi> and ſee if that will <hi>ſatiſfie</hi> him: tell him, my ſoule cries out of <hi>the grate of miſery</hi> for <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>mercy.</hi> My ſinne hath ſo ingaged my ſoule vnto God, that my <hi>heart is broken,</hi> and ſuch <hi>a ſacrifice my God will not deſpiſe.</hi> But here the Seer interrupts him. <hi>Dauid</hi> now leaue off <hi>paſsion,</hi> and arme thy ſelfe with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7288:17"/>
               <hi>patience.</hi> The <hi>decree</hi> of God is ſet down, and God will neuer <hi>grant decree vpon decree,</hi> the ſentence is paſt and may not be <hi>reuerſed,</hi> thy <hi>ſinne</hi> was great,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſo muſt be thy <hi>puniſhment. As no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell (though of thy friend) could diuert thee from the one, ſo no prayer (though neuer ſo carneſt) ſhall auert from thee the other.</hi> Herein was <hi>Gad</hi> a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>meſſenger,</hi> but a <hi>miſerable comforter.</hi> The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell <hi>ought Iſrael a ſpight</hi> and now he hath <hi>payed it</hi> them. When <hi>Nathan</hi> told <hi>Dauid</hi> of his <hi>adultery</hi> and <hi>murder,</hi> hee preſently abſolues him (vpon his repentance) <hi>The Lord hath put away thy ſinne.</hi> Why may not <hi>Gad</hi> ſay as much? <hi>Hath God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to be gracious?</hi> Oh but if we well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the child borne of that adulterous bed dyed for <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinne: <hi>and hath God forgotten to be iuſt?</hi> Thus is <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtill in a <hi>great ſtrait.</hi> Had hee beene now <hi>numbring of his dayes,</hi> he had <hi>applyed his heart to wiſedome;</hi> but now <hi>in numbring</hi> the people, his <hi>heart</hi> gaue way to <hi>folly.</hi> Now not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is he brought to the <hi>Logicians dilemma,</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to <hi>Trilemma,</hi> as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vſed in war, caſt it any way, and ſtill one poynt lies vpward, <hi>obuious</hi> to the face, and hurtfull to the foote.</p>
            <p>Now I conceiue your iudicious apprehenſions ready to foreſtall me, and already to conceiue a <hi>Doctrine</hi> which I ſhall propound, as a true borne Childe, lawfully begotten from <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe, and my premiſed diſcourſe.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:7288:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That <hi>it is a farre eaſier matter to yeeld to ſinne, then to anſwere for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sampſon</hi> was bound with <hi>ſeuen greene cordes,</hi> and hee brake them from his armes <hi>like a third. Dauid</hi> is now tyed with one twiſt of a <hi>threefold cord,</hi> and cannot get looſe. I haue heard and read of ſome <hi>Noctambulones,</hi> that haue left their beds in their ſleepe, and haue clombe vp ſuch daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous places, that waking, they could ſcarſe tell how to get downe againe: So fares it with the wilfull ſonnes of men, who being <hi>lulled aſleepe in ſinne,</hi> queſtionleſſe dreame of great ſecurity; but when their <hi>ſlumber</hi> is paſt, when the <hi>word</hi> or their <hi>conſcience</hi> ſhall awake them, then their voyce is the voyce of <hi>Dauid, Anguſtior.</hi> It may be ſayde of <hi>Sinne</hi> as the Poets ſayd of <hi>Venus;</hi>
               <q>Laeta venire Venus, triſtis abire ſolet.</q> For ſinne ſtill preſents to men <hi>vtile, iucundum,</hi> or <hi>honestum,</hi> which being by and by apprehended, Sathan ſuggeſts, man conſents, and both their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers itch till the fear be wrought, which being once effected, the <hi>pleaſure of ſinne laſting but for a ſeaſon,</hi> is withdrawne and gone. Sathan deales as <hi>Ammon</hi> did by <hi>Thamar, thruſts him out, bolts the doore,</hi> and takes no notice of the poore ſinner: Then is poore man left to himſelfe, and hath no company but a <hi>wounded conſcience,</hi> and then hee finds himſelfe in a ſtrange perplexity, in a <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtrait.</hi> And what I now (beloued) ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one ſinner, I ſay of all; <hi>When neither the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7288:18"/>voyce of reaſon can reuoke them, the bridle of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion restraine them, nor the checke of conſcience moue them, they that in the heat of ſinne will bee like Dauid vſing the vtmoſt of their liberty, ſhall in the height of puniſhment find themſelues like Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in a great ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that I may not ſeeme to want proofe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the confines of my Text, fixe we but our eies on <hi>Dauid,</hi> Tis a braue thing to number the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; it was indeed: ſo is a Waſpe a pretty thing to ſee too, but it beares a ſting in the taile. So is Sinne <hi>Mulier formoſa ſupernè, outwardly</hi> and <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> faire, but <hi>deſinit in piſcem,</hi> whatſoeuer the <hi>premiſes</hi> or the <hi>promiſes</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> may be, the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may in the end, ſay to it as dying <hi>Agrippa</hi> did to his dogge, <hi>Abi hinc in malam rem qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didiſti animam meam.</hi> See here what <hi>Dauids numbring</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> in <hi>Arithmetique</hi> came too. <hi>Addition</hi> of <hi>ſinne, Subſtraction</hi> of <hi>liberty, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of <hi>ſorrow, Diuiſion</hi> like the <hi>diuiſion of Reuben, euen great thoughts of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the manner of Worldlings to deale in ſin as Prodigals doe in expences ſpend, and call, and neuer mind the <hi>reckoning,</hi> no, nor their <hi>generall eſtate</hi> till <hi>pouertie come vpon them like an armed man.</hi> And thus the ſinner multiplies his tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions neuer minding the <hi>fearefull euent</hi> and <hi>dire Cataſtrophe</hi> of his wickedneſſe, when as indeed he ſhould like the wiſe builder, <hi>ſit downe and caſts vp his reckoning.</hi> But Satan like a cunning So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7288:18"/>ſets the beſt ſide forward, ſeparates the <hi>end</hi> from the <hi>meanes,</hi> as if <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>ſorrow,</hi> were of no acquaintance, and did not vſe to <hi>kiſſe each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> did eate the booke which the Angell gaue him, <hi>in his mouth it was as ſweet as honey,</hi> but <hi>in his belly as bitter as gall.</hi> But he that ſwallowes the <hi>bait</hi> which <hi>Satan</hi> giues him, ſhal find the <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſinne to laſt but for a ſeaſon,</hi> and in the end, <hi>bitterneſſe, bitterneſſe. Eue</hi> ſaw the <hi>apple</hi> that it was faire to the eye, but after could haue wiſhed that ſhe had neuer ſeene it. The Foxe mentioned by <hi>Horace,</hi> got eaſily into the Garner of corne, but hauing eaten his fill could not ſo ſoone get out: The hunters horne, debts liuely <hi>embleme,</hi> is eaſily <hi>entred,</hi> but hard in the <hi>egreſſe.</hi> A man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe with the tyde may eaſily <hi>ſhoot the bridge,</hi> but to returne againſt the ſtreame, <hi>hic la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, hoc opus eſt. Facilis deſcenſus Auerni:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iunenal.</note> 
               <hi>Diues</hi> may ſlip into <hi>hell</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi> without either <hi>ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> his <hi>purple garments,</hi> or <hi>pinching</hi> his well-fed <hi>belly.</hi> But then there is <hi>magnum Chaos,</hi> not a <hi>wall</hi> but a <hi>world</hi> of <hi>ſeperation</hi> betwixt him and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>The vnthrifty Tradeſman that makes the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his ſhop, the Play-houſe his Exchange, gaming his traffique, and whores his cuſtomers, when <hi>need</hi> and <hi>debt en-Counter</hi> him and his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer follies like Spiders poiſon him that he <hi>breaks,</hi> then and not till then is hee made ſenſible of his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7288:19"/>owne miſery, then his letters certifie his <hi>friends,</hi> and his <hi>tongue</hi> cries out to his <hi>Creditors, I am in a wonderfull ſtrait.</hi> Had that <hi>wealth-famous Croeſus</hi> had any more then an <hi>after-wit,</hi> he had not in his extremity needed to cry, <hi>Oh Solon, Solon.</hi> Had the Mariners beene ruled by <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 27.21.</note> they had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the wracke of their ſhip, and the loſſe of the wheat. As <hi>Martha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ieſus,</hi> Lord if thou hadſt beene here my brother had not died: ſo may I ſay of this and the like caſe, had <hi>Prometheus</hi> beene there, a <hi>wiſedome</hi> to foreſee, and <hi>foreſight</hi> to preuent, neither would any men at other time, or <hi>Dauid</hi> at this time haue fallen into this <hi>great ſtrait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how the denunciation of Gods iudgements doth <hi>amaze</hi> and <hi>perplexe</hi> the ſoules of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants when they find no expiation or atonement for ſinne! Call me now no more <hi>Dauid beloued,</hi> call me no more <hi>happy,</hi> but <hi>hated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What hard hap had <hi>Dauid</hi> that <hi>Gad</hi> the <hi>Seer</hi> was not a Pope? If ſome Chriſtian, eſpecially Antichriſtian Prince, ſhould haue the conſcience to be troubled or wounded for ſuch a ſinne as this, a <hi>Romiſh Biſhop</hi> (though neither <hi>Prophet</hi> nor <hi>Seer</hi>) would haue taught him a tricke to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided this <hi>ſtrait. Gad</hi> had no Commiſſion to <hi>pardon,</hi> but to tell <hi>Dauid</hi> of his ſinne. But now <hi>Omnia Romae vaenalia, ipſa etiam venia eſt vaenalis: Gad</hi> would not free <hi>Dauid</hi> for an Altar built in the flowre of <hi>Araunah</hi> the <hi>Iebuſite. Rome</hi> will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7288:19"/>nullifie a ſinne, and deifie a deuill for a contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution to a <hi>Ieſuite:</hi> and what? Such a ſinne as numbring the <hi>people?</hi> Nay, <hi>murder, adultery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, rebellion,</hi> and what not? Surely then a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie of <hi>Peter-pence</hi> throughout all the Land of <hi>Iudaea</hi> would haue freed them from this <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> If this be ſo that <hi>pradons</hi> are ſo frequent, I muſt intreat his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> to <hi>pardon</hi> me one thing, namely, in that I condemne and abhorre the <hi>ſowre leauen</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and leſt for want of iudgement and <hi>experience</hi> of their iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, my tongue may be thought no ſlaunder, let any man with <hi>ſounder iudgement</hi> and <hi>mature</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, perpend their practices, and hee ſhall <hi>ex vngue leonem,</hi> make an eaſie coniecture, that all their <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> their <hi>practices, cleanly coſenage, deepe hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>horrible ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſenſes now tell me that <hi>many heare this,</hi> and my Conſcience tels me that I care not <hi>who hears it:</hi> what is ſeated in my <hi>heart,</hi> were it written in my <hi>forehead,</hi> I vow that I haue loſt the vſe of that hand that ſhould euer wipe it out, and let my <hi>tongue cleaue to the roofe of my mouth,</hi> if (vpon iuſt occaſion) I ſpare or feare to tell the Church of Rome of their monſtrous enormities, and their ſtrong deluſions, wherewith they fill, the <hi>Popes coffers</hi> with gold, their Clergy with glory, and the <hi>vnderſtanding world</hi> with <hi>wonder.</hi> Durſt <hi>Gad</hi> bleſſe when God did curſe, or <hi>pronounce peace,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:7288:20"/>when God <hi>proclaimed warre:</hi> but this is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of that man of <hi>ſinne,</hi> to exalt himſelfe not onely as <hi>Lusifer,</hi> to make his <hi>ſeat with the moſt high,</hi> but to make his <hi>Apoſtolicall ſeat</hi> aboue Chriſt, and to exalt <hi>himſelfe aboue all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God. Ego &amp; Rex meus</hi> argued in the proud Cardinall little pollicy; but <hi>Ego &amp; Deus meus,</hi> argues in that <hi>Romiſh Prelate</hi> but little piety. If euer any man grow weary of that <hi>Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherein Chriſt Ieſus hath placed him,</hi> I wiſh him no other ſeruitude then a <hi>Romiſh yoake:</hi> or if any man will cancell his ſenſe and reaſon ſo farre as to be ruled by them, I dare pawne my hand that too much <hi>learning will neuer make him mad.</hi> I conclude this point with a <hi>Tridentine phraſe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Forma Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentina Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Angelicana.</note>, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall beleeue that the Pope of Rome hath any more power of pardoning ſinnes, but onely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall,</hi> (that is, where God hath firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and giuen warrant by his word to haue it pronounced by the Miniſter, <hi>Anathema eſto.</hi> The poſition is true according to our doctrine, the concluſion ſhall bee theirs that made it; I hope not for ours, but rather for their owne vſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the point thus much. <hi>Fumo pereant qui fumum vendunt.</hi> S. <hi>Peters keyes</hi> are now abuſed by <hi>popiſh pick locks,</hi> if theſe men belong to God, I beſeech him <hi>pardon</hi> them <hi>effectually</hi> for <hi>pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> ſo many, for ſo much, to ſo little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The third generall point: <hi>How Dauid tooke it, Quantapatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia pertulit.</hi> When <hi>Gad</hi> had brought
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7288:20"/>this meſſage to <hi>Dauid</hi> in the morning next his heart, we cannot but thinke that he tooke it much <hi>to heart;</hi> but yet he ſo demeaned himſelfe, that though the meſſage was <hi>grieuous</hi> yet the <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> was welcome. He deales not like the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſonne of <hi>Nebat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 13.4.1. Reg. 22.8.</note> to bid <hi>lay hands vpon</hi> the Prophet, nor doth he hate him as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah,</hi> becauſe <hi>he prophecied euill and not good,</hi> but conſiders him as <hi>the voice of a crier,</hi> and the meſſenger of the high GOD, not imputing ſo much to <hi>Gad</hi> as the troubling of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And though <hi>Dauid</hi> was not <hi>Timon-like,</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as deſirous to ſee <hi>miſery</hi> and <hi>mortality</hi> amongſt men, yet he thought this word (though harſh of it ſelfe) to bee good as being the word of the Lord, he neither can nor will challenge God as vniuſt, nor the Prophet as <hi>vnfaithfull</hi> in his <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,</hi> but to ſhew himſelfe <hi>a man after Gods owne heart,</hi> in ſaying nothing hee ſeemes to conſent vnto God as <hi>Eli</hi> did,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord let him doe what ſeemeth him good. O iuſt God, O faithfull Gad, O patient Dauid!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now could I wiſh that this patient ſpirit of <hi>Dauid</hi> were doubled vpon all the ſinfull ſonnes of this generation, who are ſo farre from patient hearing of Gods iudgements denounced, that their eares are grated, if not ſtopt at the <hi>Rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Sermon</hi> of their ſinnes: Surely, if <hi>reprofe</hi> vexe them to the heart, as it did <hi>Ahab;</hi> tydings of iudgement will break their necks,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.18.</note> as it fared with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7288:21"/>olde <hi>Eli.</hi> Is it not from hence that men are of that <hi>impatient</hi> and <hi>gun powder humour,</hi> becauſe they loue not to heare of their faults? Is it not hence that the Miniſters of God are ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged? Is it not hence that like <hi>Ionah,</hi> men had rather turne <hi>mariners</hi> then <hi>Miniſters?</hi> Without any further queſtion, hence comes <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitence,</hi> euen from <hi>impatience:</hi> hence <hi>cuſtome</hi> and <hi>obduration</hi> in Sin: (hence in a word) comes that which a religious ſoule cannot but ſee the Land deſerueth to mourn for. Some <hi>Seers</hi> are ſo choakt with a Church and a Steeple, that they cannot of all other language, pronounce <hi>Sinne</hi> in a <hi>Patron.</hi> Some dare not aduenture to diſpleaſe a <hi>great one,</hi> yea, whoſoeuer ſhall dare (like <hi>Tarquin</hi>) to ſtrike at the heads of the <hi>talleſt poppies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> or like <hi>Samuel,</hi> at the head of <hi>Agag,</hi> at their greateſt ſin, ſhal in the wiſe cenſure of ſome, be thought to babble beſide his Text, or be enrolled in the blacke booke, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue fauour at their hands. A true <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telian</hi> will neuer wonder at the irregular motion of the <hi>Orbes,</hi> if the <hi>Intelligences</hi> faile in their <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing office;</hi> nor can I wonder at the inordinate actions of this <hi>ſublunarie world,</hi> when Gods <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencers</hi> dare not tell <hi>Iſrael of her ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.1.</note> 
               <hi>and Iudah of her tranſgreſsions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if I durſt aduenture, I could put ſome into <hi>a wonderfull Strait,</hi> and bring ſome ſoules before the iuſtice of God, whom the <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> hath openly <hi>quitt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7288:21"/>
            <p> Should I ſay that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> is turned a great Patron of <hi>Benefices</hi> amongſt vs, and that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome-ſeruant <hi>Quid dabis</hi> were a diſpoſer of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, I know not how this Age would take it: Should I ſay that ſome gallants weare Vicars cloathes, or ſpend the Clergies bookes in yellow ruffes, they may perhaps, haue <hi>pepper in the noſe,</hi> as well as Cloues in their <hi>bands.</hi> Or ſhould I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the generall Apoſtacie of the world, from that good eſtate and plight wherein our Fathers haue knowne it, ſome <hi>Stoicall Athenian</hi> may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as his wiſedome thinketh, aske <hi>what will this babbler ſay?</hi> If they or any of them will needes know, then this I ſay (and yet not I, but others <hi>whoſe ſhooe latchets I am not worthy to looſe</hi>) that for the particular ſinne of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> all that is ſo gotten, is <hi>aurum Tholoſſanum,</hi> and that all the bread at ſuch Patrons tables are <hi>cheat loaues.</hi> And for the generall eſtate of the whole world (as one ſayd bitterly of <hi>Rome</hi>) <hi>probabilius est ſtrui nouam quam emendare antiquam,</hi> more like to haue a new Rome built, then the old to be amended: ſo I ſay of the <hi>world,</hi> that it is more probable ſooner to ſee it changed in <hi>ſubſtance</hi> then in <hi>manners;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that (ſo farre as I ſee) the world is likely ſooner to ceaſe to <hi>be,</hi> then to <hi>be wicked:</hi> and hence is <hi>noſtri mundi calamitas,</hi> that men had rather ten times commit one ſinne, then once heare of ten ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke all in good part that <hi>Gad</hi> ſpake,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7288:22"/>though it were neuer ſo harſh, and blamed none but himſelfe for being brought into this <hi>Strait:</hi> I would that all that heare me this day were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not <hi>almoſt,</hi> but <hi>altogether</hi> ſuch as <hi>Dauid,</hi> then would <hi>Herod</hi> heare the reproofe of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt gladly,</hi> then would euery man ſo <hi>heare the word,</hi> as to <hi>amend his life according to the word,</hi> then would <hi>God be honoured, his Miniſters comforted,</hi> and <hi>the World well amended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>deaſe Adder will not heare</hi> when wee <hi>charme</hi> the world with zeale and diſcretion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily <hi>vnited,</hi> then the Lord commands to cry <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud and ſpare not, to lift vp our voyces like a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.1:</note> and to deale as that oppreſſed widow, moue them with vnceſſant preaching, and to be bolde as Lyons in Gods cauſe. Let <hi>Peter</hi> tell <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> plainely,
<note place="margin">Act. 8.23. Acts 13.10.</note> that he is <hi>in the gall of bitterneſse, and the bond of iniquitie:</hi> Let <hi>Paul</hi> tell <hi>Elymas</hi> the ſorcerer that he is the child of the <hi>diuell,</hi> if he be full of all wickedneſſe; We muſt learne of <hi>Gad,</hi> not <hi>ſpare to ſpeake,</hi> though we <hi>ſpare to ſpeed.</hi> And all godly and conſcionable hearers muſt learne of <hi>Dauid to heare with quietnes, to beare with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and <hi>to mend with willingnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As <hi>Dauid chides not</hi> with <hi>Gad,</hi> ſo he <hi>quarrels not</hi> with <hi>God;</hi> and though (as our Prouerb goes) <hi>loſers muſt haue leaue to ſpeake;</hi> yet hee (though (I ſuppoſe) <hi>his heart waxed hote within him) neuer ſpake with his lips</hi> to iuſtifie himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> Thus might his Pharifaicall thoughts haue ſuggeſted: Ah my
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7288:22"/>Lord, I haue a long time gone in and out before this thy people: O Lord thou knoweſt that I loue thee, and haue with all my heart ſticken to thy teſtimonies, I haue had ſo great a care of my wayes, as not to offend in my tongue: O thou Lord, good and gracious, full of mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, is thy mercy cleane forgotten? or ſhall all the former paſſage of my life be too little to expiate one ſmall ſinne? Thou madeſt proffer of mercy to <hi>fiue Cities,</hi> for <hi>ten righteous,</hi> and wilt thou not ſpare <hi>one</hi> man for <hi>one</hi> ſinne? Thou that pardoneſt ſuch a number of ſinnes to thy people, wilt thou not pardon ſuch a ſinne as <hi>numbring of the people?</hi> Thus might <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeem to haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Apud. Linium.</note> 
               <hi>Tullus</hi> an interpreter of the Law hauing pleaded for the life of <hi>Horatius</hi> (who had murdered his Siſter) and not preuailing, the Father of this <hi>Horatius</hi> demands of the <hi>Romans,</hi> whether they could lead his ſonne to death, but his owne demerits and valiant acts would euen giue a dumbe ſhew to haue his life ſaued: So might <hi>humane iudgement</hi> (had it now beene Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate haue pleaded for <hi>Dauid,</hi> but it would not haue preuailed, nor haue beene a <hi>ſufficient baile,</hi> to haue freed Dauid from this <hi>vnſuſpected Sinne,</hi> and <hi>vnexpected ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>he that hath an eare to heare,</hi> a <hi>heart</hi> to <hi>conſider,</hi> and a <hi>memory</hi> to <hi>remember,</hi> cannot in <hi>ſenſe</hi> but <hi>heare,</hi> in <hi>reaſon</hi> he muſt <hi>vnderſtand,</hi> and (vnleſſe he will forget himſelfe) remember this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7288:23"/>for his <hi>instruction,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That the waight of mans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is not ſufficient by many graines to counterpoiſe the burden of one wilfull ſinne if God be extreame to enter into iudgement with the Sonnes of men, though they be ſuch as are indeed the Sonnes of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How faire ſoeuer the preceedent part of their liues haue been both in their <hi>publique</hi> and <hi>priuate</hi> callings, yet that great <hi>King of heauen</hi> who can eſpie one man amongſt <hi>many without a wedding garment:</hi> can in his <hi>omniſcience,</hi> and may, and doth often in his <hi>iuſtice</hi> enter into <hi>iudgement</hi> for the commiſſion of one ſinne, eſpecially if wilfull, as was this of <hi>Dauid:</hi> as we ſee in the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2.2.</note> though laudable for <hi>her workes, her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, her patience, and perſeuerance,</hi> yet there is a <hi>ſomething</hi> that God hath againſt her for which he will <hi>remoue the Candleſticke out of his place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhe repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many plankes</hi> well pind and calkt, make the Ship to float: one and but <hi>one leake</hi> will ſincke it. <hi>One wound</hi> may ſtrike <hi>Goliah</hi> dead as well as <hi>three and twenty</hi> did <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sam. 17.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sueton.</hi> Iudg. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>One Dalilah</hi> will doe <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> as much ſpight as all the <hi>Philiſtims. One wheele</hi> broken ſpoiles all the <hi>whole clocke. One veines bleeding</hi> will let out the <hi>vitall ſpirits</hi> as well as <hi>more.</hi> One flie will ſpoile a whole boxe of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">1 Reg. 49.</note> One hearb <hi>Colloquintida</hi> ſpoiles all the pottage. One Apple loſt <hi>Adam</hi> the pleaſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.27.</note> One licke of honey endangered the life of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7288:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ionathan.</hi> One <hi>Achan</hi> was a trouble to all <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ 7.25.</note> One <hi>Ionah,</hi> if faulty,
<note place="margin">Ionah 17.</note> is lading too heauy for a whole Shippe. And one ſinne is <hi>enough</hi> to procure Gods anger, and <hi>too much</hi> for a man to commit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Now that God may not be challenged of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iniuſtice, as though hee would eaſily picke a quarrell with men,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.10.</note> heare what S. <hi>Iames</hi> auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>That he that failes in one point, is guilty of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſtone caſt into the midſt of the water, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles euery part of the water, euen to the very banke.</p>
            <p>But I ſpeake not this as if any man hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted one ſinne, ſhould in a deſperate moode, aduenture the committing of more, becauſe when he hath done all, he can but be found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo puniſhed. God forbid that any man ſhould heare like <hi>Malchus,</hi> with his <hi>left eare</hi> only. But this is my drift (if it were poſſible) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre and affright the hearer from countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or giuing the leaſt entertainment to the leaſt ſinne whatſoeuer, or the leaſt motion of that ſinne.</p>
            <p>As it was ſpoken in another caſe, <hi>Ex peſsimo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ne catulus quidem educandus:</hi> So I ſay, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>purity</hi> of God, who can abide <hi>no ſin,</hi> and his <hi>iuſtice,</hi> which may puniſh <hi>euery</hi> ſin, let vs not giue way to <hi>any</hi> ſin. And if God thus take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>one</hi> ſinne, let vs take heed of <hi>all</hi> ſinne: as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7288:24"/>being accomptable for in Gods ſight. One ſinne, a ſmall ſinne in mans iudgement, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and prouoke God to ſend a heauy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we may here obſerue the impartiall hand of God: may not <hi>Dauid</hi> be ſpared for a ſinne? true it is, <hi>veniam laeſo numine nullus habet. Conijah</hi> if he offend, <hi>though he were the Signet on Gods right hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22.24.</note> 
               <hi>God will cut him off.</hi> Neuer was any ſinne committed, but muſt be puniſhed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>ſinner,</hi> or in the <hi>Sauiour:</hi> and though it be <hi>quoad aeternam poenam, pardoned</hi> and <hi>puniſhed</hi> in the <hi>Saniour,</hi> yet it ſtands with the iuſtice of God, temporally to puniſh a <hi>little ſinne</hi> in a <hi>great Saint,</hi> yea one onely ſinne, though in his owne children. <hi>Dauid</hi> is noted but for one ſinne before, and for that one his one <hi>child borne in adulterie</hi> died. Which kind of proceeding in almighty God, though it may ſeeme harſh and <hi>bitter as the waters of Marah,</hi> yet hence it doth receiue its dulcoration, in that it proceeds from a <hi>bleſſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>attributes</hi> in almighty God, <hi>his iuſtice, his holineſſe, his wiſedome, Iuſtice</hi> puniſhing one ſinne, his <hi>holineſſe</hi> brooking no ſinne, his <hi>wiſedome</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting many ſinnes, all concurring in one act of puniſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> His <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> that <hi>holy, holy, holy Lord God of Sabaoth</hi> requires <hi>holy</hi> thoughts, <hi>holy</hi> words, <hi>holy</hi> actions, and therefore any thing that is <hi>vnholy,</hi> muſt needs <hi>grieue his holy ſpirit:</hi> and that not only
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7288:24"/>in <hi>Cain, Saul, Iudas, Iulian, &amp;c.</hi> veſſels of <hi>wrath,</hi> and ſonnes of <hi>perdition,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>veſſels</hi> of <hi>honor</hi> &amp; the <hi>heyres of grace;</hi> nay further, taking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the matter more hainouſly at their hands. As we reade of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who of ſo many wounds giuen him at his death, complained of none but of <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and thou my ſon!</hi> So for <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to play the harlot, the <hi>holy City</hi> become <hi>a cage of vncleant birds,</hi> he will neuer endure.</p>
            <p>As one good motion and inclination in the young Man made Chriſt <hi>begin to loue him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> and the ſparkes of goodneſſe ſhining were wel-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto him (though the young man were not right.) So on the contrary, one euill admitted and perpetrated by a child of God, makes God in his holineſſe diſlike and diſtaſte (though not abſolutely and finally the <hi>perſon,</hi> yet the <hi>ſinne</hi>) by whomſoeuer committed, nor can there bee any peace betwixt a righteous God and a <hi>wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His <hi>wiſedome</hi> who (ſeeing ſinne the daughter of impunity, and the <hi>fruitfull mother</hi> of ſuch a <hi>damned brood,</hi>) doth <hi>principiis obſtare,</hi> killing this Cockatrice in the egge, and preuenting this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and farre-creeping fire before it run too farre and rage too ſore, dealing as a wiſe father with his child, who breakes him of his <hi>vntoward diſpoſition</hi> before it grow to a <hi>ſetled habit:</hi> men are of that diſpoſition which God complaines of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7288:25"/>held my peace, and thou thoughtst I was euen ſuch a one as thy ſelfe:</hi> and therefore it followes, <hi>I will reprooue thee, and ſet before thy face in order the things that thou haſt done.</hi> If hee ſhould not <hi>aurem vellere,</hi> and make his iudgements the <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's</hi> of ſinne, either the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> would be thought not to <hi>regard it,</hi> or the reuenging <hi>arme to be ſhortened,</hi> or elſe that God laying aſide his holineſſe, did in part begin to approue thoſe of which his ſoule hath ſaid heretofore <hi>I hate them.</hi> The leaſt of which three gaps being layd open, the <hi>Gadarens Swine ranne</hi> not ſo faſt and <hi>headlong into the Sea,</hi> as men would poaſt and precipitate themſelues to the bottomleſſe <hi>gulfe</hi> of <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> His <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> who though he loue his <hi>Saints</hi> with <hi>an Eternall loue,</hi> yet is not bound to the tollerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the leaſt, nor the conniuencie at any ſinne: but on Gods part, that he may declare his iuſtice, and on their parts, that they are <hi>Sonnes, and not baſtards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note> doth <hi>afflict, correct, and chaſtiſe</hi> them: and though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>finall and deſtroying puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> be properly the portion of the wicked, yet his iudgements <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for inſtruction,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for warning</hi> and <hi>example,</hi> are no more often then iuſtly let looſe vpon his owne Children; and albeit God hath promiſed <hi>to ſpare them,</hi> yet hee will <hi>but ſpare as a man doth his Sonne,</hi> not to free from a <hi>fatherly correction,</hi> but from <hi>ſcourges</hi> and <hi>whips,</hi> which are onely <hi>for the backs of fooles;</hi> and <hi>wounds,</hi> which are for <hi>the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7288:25"/>hairie ſcalpes of ſuch as goe on in their wickedneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 68.21.</note> So then, his <hi>holineſſe,</hi> his <hi>iuſtice,</hi> and his <hi>wiſdome</hi> being the mouing cauſes of this action, we muſt in ſuch a caſe with <hi>Iob, lay our hand vpon our mouth,</hi> and with old <hi>Eli,</hi> reſt contented: <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>if iudgement beginne at the houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.18. Pſal. 130.3.</note> and if <hi>the righteous ſhall not be ſpared, what ſhall become of them, what ſhall be their end that obey not the Goſpell of God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.15:</note> 
               <hi>If thou Lord be extreame to marke what is done amiſſe:</hi> yea by thy Saints ſo <hi>deare and pretious in thine eyes:</hi> yea the very <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of thine eyes:</hi> Oh what a fearefull expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is it of <hi>iudgement and fierce indignation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.27:</note> 
               <hi>which ſhall deſtroy the aduerſaries of God?</hi> If <hi>Dauid</hi> fell into this <hi>great ſtrait</hi> for <hi>one Sinne,</hi> what ſhall be done to <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Tyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 1.9.12. &amp; 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>for three tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions and for foure?</hi> but <hi>fire, a destroying fire,</hi> which ſhall conſume <hi>Teman of the Edomites, Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioth of the Moabites,</hi> and the <hi>walls</hi> of <hi>Tyrus?</hi> If <hi>Dauid be auenged ſeuen-fold,</hi> ſurely the vngodly <hi>that drinke in ſinne like water, and draw iniquitie with cordes of vanity, ſhall be auenged ſeuenty times ſeuen fold.</hi> If this be done to <hi>a green tree, what ſhall be done to a drie tree?</hi> Conſider, and I beſeech you againe conſider and remember this, <hi>you that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God:</hi> you whoſe liues are nothing but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall rebellion, and <hi>grieuing of the ſpirit of God.</hi> To you I ſpeake <hi>quorum etiam laudabilis vita damnabilis eſt, ſi cum Dauide conferatur:</hi> thoſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7288:26"/>whoſe moſt laudable part of their liues are odious if any way paralleld with <hi>Dauid.</hi> If no ſighes, or teares, or prayers could expiate his ſin, or diuert Gods iuſtly conceiued diſpleaſure, I ſay to them and yet not I, but the ſpirit of God himſelf, that albeit they ſhall <hi>hide themſelues in dens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>and in the rocks of the mountains, that neither rocks nor moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines (though they ſhould fall vpon them) ſhalbe able to hide them from the face of him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe.</hi> If the meditation of this were ſeated in the hearts of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and wicked men, although no <hi>ſon-like,</hi> yet euen a <hi>ſlauiſh feare</hi> would curbe and bridle the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed colts of the world, when they ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how in euery ſin, they doe but <hi>heape vp wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>and reuelation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement of God.</hi> This being duly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>he that is vniuſt,</hi> would ſcarſe continue <hi>vniuſt ſtill; nor he that is filthy to be filthy ſtill:</hi> But <hi>hee that is holy would be holy ſtill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De libero arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15</note> 
               <hi>he that is righteous would be righteous ſtill:</hi> For as <hi>Auguſtine, Qui non reddit Deo faciendo quod debet, reddet ei pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo quod debet.</hi> Whoſo doth not what he <hi>ſhould,</hi> ſhall ſuffer what he would not.</p>
            <p>But leſt while I keepe <hi>Dauid</hi> in this <hi>ſtrait,</hi> I ſhould runne too much at large, I come now in the laſt place, to the <hi>bailing</hi> of this <hi>priſoner</hi> out of the tedious <hi>little-eaſe,</hi> and to ſhew vnto you in the fourth circumſtance propounded, how he freed himſelf, and with how much wiſedom.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7288:26"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Qua prudentia euaſerit? Redimit ſe ſapiens captum quam queat minimo.</hi> When <hi>Iulian</hi> was oppoſed by the hand of heauen, he was ſo obdurate in his Sinne, that <hi>Viciſti Gelilaee</hi> and his bloud came out together; this was horrible <hi>obſtinacie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 31 4.</note> When <hi>Saul</hi> was in a <hi>Strait,</hi> he fell on his owne ſword and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that was <hi>deſperation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 28.22</note> When <hi>Ahaz</hi> felt the hand of God, he <hi>ſinned more and more;</hi> this was flat <hi>rebellion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> None of theſe courſes like or pleaſe <hi>Dauid,</hi> but as <hi>Theſeus</hi> in the <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> gate out by the helpe of <hi>Ariadnes Clew;</hi> ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> by the guidance and direction of the Spirit of God, and by <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Wiſedome, freed himſelfe from this great <hi>Strait.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>Hebrewes</hi> imagine,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the laſt word of <hi>Gad</hi> in propounding, gaue <hi>Dauid</hi> ſome hint and direction for his choyce, becauſe the ſame word <hi>Dabhar,</hi> with ſome changing of points, ſignifieth the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> which in <hi>Gads</hi> ſpeech ſignifieth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed onely, <hi>What word ſhall I carry him that ſent me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Willet in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> and this by a reuerend and learned Diuine of our owne is worthily refuſed; becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> was a prudent and wiſe man, and needed not any direction for ſuch a choyce. But now <hi>Dauid</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard put to it, thinkes with himſelfe: As I haue done fooliſhly in <hi>committing the ſin,</hi> I would faine deale wiſely in the <hi>choyce of the puniſhment.</hi> As hee that is immured within ſome high wall, will make choyce of the loweſt part to leape ouer.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:7288:27"/>
            <p> Thus then he reſolues; I am indeede <hi>ſtraited, Lupum auribus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneo:</hi> Now as <hi>ex duobus malis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> ſo <hi>ex tribus minimum eſt eligendum.</hi> If I chooſe <hi>Warre,</hi> I feare many enemies to offend me: now <hi>melius eſt timere vnum quam multos.</hi> If I chooſe <hi>Peſtilence</hi> I feare but one. If I chooſe <hi>Famine,</hi> the poore will pay for it: If <hi>Warre,</hi> the weakeſt go to the walls. Now <hi>Gad</hi> I am reſolued, tell the Lord that ſent thee, this is my anſwere: <hi>Let vs now fall into the hands of God, for his mercies are great, and not into the hands of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which choyce we cannot but obſerue; firſt, <hi>Dauids Charitie,</hi> ſecondly his <hi>Piety,</hi> thirdly his <hi>Wiſedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charity:</hi> Oftentimes (yea and too often) <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt Reges, plectuntur Achiui. Dauid</hi> had now of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, theſe <hi>poore ſheepe of Iſrael, what had they done?</hi> Hee offers himſelfe, and his fathers houſe, verſe 17. <hi>for a peace offering:</hi> but ſith it is <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne malum,</hi> by Gods immutable decree, he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that euill wherein hee may be <hi>ſocius doloris,</hi> willing indeed to beare a part in this doleful <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy,</hi> neuer deſiring like the <hi>Mariners,</hi> to ſcape a generall danger in a <hi>cock-boat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 27.30.</note> but offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a ſharer in the preſent danger, by <hi>chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an euill</hi> which doth <hi>aequo pede pulſare paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tabernas, Regum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turres.</hi> We read of <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Albert,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. Petit. hiſt. Netherlands. Iuven. Sat.</hi> 10.</note> that at <hi>Newport battaile</hi> in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> hee forſooke his armie, and fled to <hi>Bruſsels:</hi> and of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> that he fledde <hi>vix vna naue, cruentis
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7288:27"/>fluctibus, &amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Dauid</hi> more charitablie ſtayes the brunt, and equals his weale or woe with his ſubiects, whom his Sinne had brought to this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His <hi>Pietie: Warre</hi> would without reſiſtance, haue prooued but a <hi>maſſacre:</hi> and this (now <hi>French-tricke</hi>) would haue made the <hi>field a ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and turned the <hi>flouriſhing</hi> cities of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a place of <hi>skulls,</hi> and into <hi>Aceld ama,</hi> a <hi>field of bloud.</hi> And the inſulting enemie would haue ſpread their banners <hi>in defiance of the Lord:</hi> this would haue cut <hi>Dauid</hi> to the heart, to haue ſeene not onely the place of his <hi>honour</hi> made a reproach, but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his own <hi>honor</hi> into <hi>ſhame:</hi> for though his enemies had beene but the <hi>rod of Gods furie,</hi> they would haue aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed their victory to the power and mercy of their gods (as once the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did to <hi>Dagon</hi>) and ſo haue robbed God of the <hi>honour due vnto his Name:</hi> which <hi>Dauid</hi> moſt deerely tendring,
<note place="margin">Iud. 16.24.</note> choſe rather to haue God the auenger of his own quarrell, then to haue <hi>the daughters of the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed</hi> either reuell in the ruins of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or take away the glory of God, which <hi>he will giue to none other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> His <hi>Wiſedome:</hi> not grounding his <hi>choyce</hi> vpon <hi>Sands,</hi> as a <hi>fooliſh builder,</hi> or vpon <hi>ſtat pro ratione voluntas,</hi> like an vntuterd moraliſt; nor yet vpon a bare <hi>Theorie</hi> or <hi>contemplation,</hi> as the <hi>naturaliſt;</hi> but vpon a ſetled and grounded <hi>experience</hi> of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7288:28"/>mercies of God: Which he knowes ſo well, that his <hi>knowledge</hi> doth <hi>apprehend them,</hi> and his tongue dare boldly <hi>pronounce them,</hi> that <hi>his mercies are great,</hi> or (as the <hi>Originall</hi>) in the diſcrete quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, <hi>they are many.</hi> Nor doth hee chooſe to fall into the hands of God, becauſe <hi>his iudgements are few,</hi> but becauſe <hi>his mercies are many.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> But why now ſpeakes <hi>Dauid</hi> of Gods <hi>mercies,</hi> when God is now bent to puniſh? and it ſeemes, <hi>hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to be gracious.</hi> Becauſe that God in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of adminiſtring iuſtice, and puniſhing his children, doth ſhew and ſet forth no ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his goodneſſe and mercy. If any ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund (as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in another caſe) <hi>how can theſe things be?</hi> doe but <hi>ſee,</hi> and you ſhall <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;</hi> doe but <hi>obſerue,</hi> and you will <hi>conſent,</hi> That the motto of the moſt afflicted ſoule may be, <hi>The mercies of our God are great.</hi> The rather for theſe reaſons following:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the act of <hi>puniſhing,</hi> God puniſheth a little, and pardoneth a great deale, not ſuiting his plagues according to our deſerts, for then wee ſhould <hi>be conſumed:</hi> but as a louing and mercifull Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, when the debtor owes an <hi>hundred,</hi> bids him take his pen and write <hi>fiftie,</hi> or at the moſt, <hi>foure ſcore:</hi> nay indeede not taking ſo much as <hi>fiue</hi> in the <hi>hundred</hi> of his debtors, cutting off onely the <hi>hemme of our garment,</hi> or <hi>the ſkirt of our rayment,</hi> when we owe vnto him our ſoules as forfeit by reaſon of our tranſgreſſion. Any ſinne committed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7288:28"/>againſt our <hi>infinite God,</hi> deſerues <hi>an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment:</hi> If God therefore ſhall abate <hi>eternitie,</hi> and ſend vs <hi>puniſhment,</hi> is not <hi>his mercy great?</hi> If when we deſerue <hi>many stripes,</hi> he giues vs but <hi>ſtripes,</hi> is not his mercy <hi>great?</hi> for man in this kind, would haue had <hi>the vtmoſt farthing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the end of <hi>puniſhing,</hi> farre is it from God to ayme at the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of his people; nay hee aymes at their <hi>inſtruction,</hi> that they might learne <hi>to keepe his Statutes and Commandements.</hi> And whereas an enemie would <hi>funditus delere nocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</hi> that his name,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.8.</note> nor <hi>the name of Iſrael might be had no more in remembrance, Gods wayes are not as mens wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God indeede ſometimes deſtroyes the body that he may ſaue the ſoule; he puniſheth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with the <hi>world,</hi> that <hi>they may not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the world:</hi> Others take vengeance out of <hi>hatred,</hi> God out of his <hi>loue, Caſtigans non quod odio habeat, ſed quod amet.</hi> The originall of this action being ſo farre different, muſt of neceſſitie ſuppoſe a contrary end. <hi>A great Armada</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing, kills vp all. <hi>A Powder-treaſon vndiſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> blowes vp all: <hi>Ab vno intenditur ruina, ab altero doctrina.</hi> God meanes good, man meanes miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the manner of <hi>puniſhing, Gods mercies are great.</hi> Albeit the <hi>iuſtice</hi> of God be mooued, and his <hi>patience</hi> prouoked: and though with men, <hi>Laeſa patientia vertitur in furorem,</hi> Patience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7288:29"/>turnes to furie: and yet not <hi>furor breuis,</hi> a ſhort furie, but an irreconcileable hatred: Yet God (though offended) will not alwaies be <hi>chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.9.</note> 
               <hi>neither keepeth he his anger for euer:</hi> yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>he whet his ſword, and bend his bow, and make ready his arrowes,</hi> yet a poore ſoule may haue a preſent <hi>appeale, a Deo irato, ad Deum pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> being ſo appeaſable and facile, vnto ſuch as ſhall vpon the bended knees of their ſoules ſue out <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>pardon,</hi> by renouncing of their ſinnes, and relying vpon his <hi>great mercies.</hi> Nay, the Lord himſelfe of himſelfe, in this preſent <hi>plague,</hi> without any intreaty (to the comfort of penitent ſinners I ſpeake it) did commaund the <hi>deſtroying Angell</hi> to hold his hand, as grieuing to ſee the miſery of his people: and that ſo ſoon, that <hi>Dauid</hi> had not time to offer any <hi>ſacrifice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatorie,</hi> but at the ceaſing of the plague, a <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will offering gratulatory,</hi> for the remouall of ſo heauy a iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In this very puniſhment, the Lord is more then iuſtifiable <hi>in all his wayes, and holy in all his works,</hi> and had he now decreed that whatſoeuer was <hi>left of the famine, the ſword ſhould deſtroy, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer was left of the ſword, the peſtilence ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy,</hi> and ſo haue ſent althoſe three <hi>furies</hi> of <hi>hell</hi> at once to haue aſſailed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what curſed Atheiſt durſt haue ſaid or thought, but the <hi>Lord is iuſte:</hi> but now hehold him alſo <hi>mercifull,</hi> he <hi>opens</hi> but one <hi>Seale,</hi> ſends but one puniſhment. Nor is that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7288:29"/>poſitiuely ſet downe, or cald out by name, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter combat with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but left <hi>arbitrary</hi> to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: Chuſe one:</hi> It is much if <hi>beggers</hi> may be <hi>chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> more if <hi>ſinners. Traian</hi> intending the death of <hi>Seneca,</hi> bade him make choyce of the manner of his death: <hi>Traian</hi> was cruell in his <hi>decree,</hi> though kind in ſuch a <hi>proffer.</hi> God not cruell, but mercifull vnto all his <hi>workes,</hi> makes <hi>Dauid</hi> heere pronounce the ſentence of iudgement. <hi>Chuſe one:</hi> Is not heere great mercy? Now <hi>Seneca</hi> in his wiſedome choſe the eaſieſt to <hi>bleed to death in a bath:</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> now hauing conſidered the <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, great</hi> of themſelues, but yet greater, if compared with the <hi>mercies of men,</hi> chuſeth to <hi>fall into the hands of God,</hi> who is <hi>iuſt</hi> and <hi>mercifull</hi> in the <hi>act</hi> of <hi>puniſhment, gracious</hi> and <hi>mercifull</hi> in the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>puniſhment: patient</hi> and <hi>merciful</hi> in his <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and laſtly, exceeding <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull</hi> in this very <hi>puniſhment.</hi> As the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God may iuſtly prouoke our <hi>admiration,</hi> ſo <hi>Dauids</hi> wiſe <hi>choyce</hi> may be iuſtified (as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did that of <hi>Mary</hi>) <hi>he choſe the better part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>to fall into Gods hands, whoſe mercies are great.</hi> Can we now but wonder at <hi>Dauids choyce</hi> when (all things conſidered) <hi>ipſa iuſtitia Dei ſit miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi> Fooliſh and vnfortunate was the <hi>ingreſſe</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſinne, but moſt prudent and happy the <hi>euaſion</hi> out of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But how was it ſo happy, ſeeing the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (to affright from Sinne) determines and defines
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7288:30"/>
               <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.31</note> After that I haue ſerued neceſſity in the <hi>reconciling</hi> theſe two places, I muſt obey the time. Thus then briefely.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>1</label> Two things muſt here be conſidered, Firſt, of what maner of ſinne and ſinners the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<note place="margin">Willet vbi ſupra.</note> namely, of thoſe <hi>that tread vnder foote the Sonne of God, that count the bloud of the Couenant wherewith he was ſanctified, an vnholy thing, and haue deſpited the ſpirit of grace,</hi> as appeareth <hi>verſe</hi> 29. But <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe and theirs are not alike: his was a <hi>Sinne,</hi> but of a child of God; it was a <hi>Sinne,</hi> but of <hi>infirmity:</hi> Theirs are <hi>Sinnes,</hi> but <hi>Sinnes</hi> of <hi>reprobates:</hi> theirs are <hi>Sinnes,</hi> but of that nature, that the firſt is <hi>intolerable,</hi> the ſecond is like vnto it, <hi>abhominable,</hi> and the third as <hi>Chriſt the truth</hi> it ſelfe hath pronounced, <hi>impardonable, either in this world, or in the world to come:</hi> That is (ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Bellarmines</hi> patience) they ſhall not haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſenſe or feeling of pardon in this world,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Explic. locus Mat.</hi> 12.32.</note> or benefite of remiſſion of ſinnes in the world to come: or (as our Church) in ſhorter termes, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi> Here then is the caſe; It is one caſe to appeare before a temporal Iudge as a <hi>malefactor</hi> in wrong or violence to my <hi>neighbour,</hi> which may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and auoyded by ſome legall meanes: or if not, the puniſhment may extend to loſſe of goods or good name, and not touch life. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother caſe, when a man ſhall appeare as guilty of that roaring ſin of <hi>Treaſon againſt</hi> his <hi>Soueraigne</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:7288:30"/>(a monſtrous ſinne, worthy ten thouſand deaths, if a malefactor had ſo many liues) what a wofull and fearefull caſe is this? So it is one thing to ſinne, and another thing to ſinne <hi>with ſo high an hand,</hi> and herein it is <hi>a fearefull thing to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the liuing God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Apoſtle ſpeakes not of <hi>temporall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> but <hi>eternall.</hi> Now in eternall iudgement, it is a moſt fearefull thing indeed, in regard of the vnlimited power of God,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.5. Mat. 10.28.</note> 
               <hi>who is able after he hath killed, to deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell fire:</hi> yea I ſay againe, <hi>him feare:</hi> but as for temporall iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it is farre better to put our ſelues vpon <hi>God,</hi> then vpon <hi>our countrey: For there is mercy with the Lord. Homo</hi> is called <hi>homini lupus,</hi> but God is <hi>homini Deus:</hi> But becauſe <hi>contraria iuxta ſe poſita, clarius eluceſcunt,</hi> ſee we in a word, what the mercies of men are: I remember their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, daſhing of Infants braines againſt the ſtones: I remember (and that with amazement) ripping vp of women with child:
<note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> I remember the lamentable <hi>ſiege</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when the <hi>glory of the Land</hi> the holy Citie, the <hi>glory</hi> of that Citie the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Temple Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> was vtterly ruined and waſted by the hands of mercileſſe <hi>Romans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Franc. Petit. hiſt. Netherlands</note> I remember that French Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Bordett</hi> choſe rather to be ſhott by a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettier of his owne Company, then to fall into the hands of the bloudy <hi>Duke of Alua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now hoping that all this Chriſtian Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7288:31"/>came hither to learne: I beſeech you learne theſe two things of one whoſe face perhaps few of you haue ſeen before, and it may be neuer ſhall ſee hereafter, eſpecially in ſo publike a place as this <hi>holy Mount</hi> where on I ſtand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if the worſt of our condition ſhall betide this ſinfull Nation of ours, namely <hi>to ſuffer for our ſinne,</hi> let vs ſay to God as <hi>Zeba and Zalmanna</hi> did to <hi>Gideon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>Fall thou vpon vs, for as is the man ſo is his ſtrength.</hi> So Lord if wee muſt ſuffer, <hi>fall thou vpon vs, for as is the Lord ſo is his mercy. England</hi> is encompaſſed with the <hi>Sea,</hi> which for the moſt part is beneficiall, though ſometimes hurtfull: <hi>encompaſſed</hi> with Gods <hi>mercies,</hi> which are alwayes helpfull, neuer hurtfull: <hi>encompaſſed</hi> with <hi>enemies,</hi> alwayes hurtfull, neuer helpfull. If the Sea break in, the worſt is death, and no more: if our <hi>enemies</hi> breake in, if they preuaile, what proud inſulting, what cruell tormenting? what ſhall be wanting to make vs miſerable? Lord wee haue ſinned with our Fathers, and haue deſerued <hi>the vialls of thy fierce wrath:</hi> But O Lord <hi>doe thou correct vs,</hi> for thou wilt not doe it <hi>in thine anger, nor chaſten vs in thine indignation:</hi> but neuer giue vs ouer into the hands of men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Seeing our originall is ſinfull as well as all the Sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> and that wee haue deſerued Gods heauy iudgements as well as others, Oh now, ſeeing God hath withheld his reuenging hand ſo long, let vs learne that counſell of <hi>Daniel</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:7288:31"/>to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.24.</note> to <hi>break off our ſinnes by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and our iniquity by mercy, and let there be an healing of our error.</hi> Let vs in the name of God turne before it be too late, leſt wee repent when it is too late. Lord open our eyes that wee may ſee the <hi>day of our viſitation,</hi> and preuent that fearefull doome of hauing <hi>theſe good things hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from our eyes. O fortunatos nimium bona ſi ſua noſſent Britannos,</hi> we diſtaſt the enioying of that whoſe loſſe our Chriſtian neighbours bewaile. The Chriſtians in <hi>Polonia</hi> cry out for ayde: The Proteſtants in <hi>Bohemia</hi> groane vnder a heauie and intolerable burden: The Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> ſend many ſighes to heauen for <hi>peace</hi> or <hi>bare ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Happy <hi>Britaines,</hi> wee ſit vnder our owne Vines, and our owne Fig-trees (God of his mercy continue it.) Let vs not cut off our welfare by our wickedneſſe. Wee haue not <hi>Famine,</hi> but <hi>Plenty;</hi> not <hi>Warre,</hi> but <hi>Peace;</hi> not <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> but <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Soundneſſe.</hi> Now in a word, as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> dealt with <hi>Victory,</hi> clipping of her wings, that ſhe might neuer flie from them againe, ſo let vs doe with our happineſſe, <hi>Happineſſe it ſelfe!</hi> Seeing it may (God knowes how ſoone) be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from vs, ſtay her flight by thankfulneſſe and obedience. If there be amongſt vs that thinke happineſſe abſent, I wiſh them to <hi>prepare her way and make her paths ſtraight, that ſhee may come in and dwell with vs.</hi> Or if ſhe be amongſt vs (as the <hi>God onely wiſe and immortall knoweth that</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
